<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discription of the contrey of Aphrique the fyrst part of the worlde, with the cituation of al the countreys together, with the perticuler maners lawes, and ceremonies, of dyuers people inhabityng in the same part. Translated out of Frenche into Englyshe by Wyllyam Prat of London, the fyrst daye of the newe yere, M.CCCCC.LIIII. Rede it dylygently, marke it perfectly, reuolue it thorowly, beare it equally, beholde the auctours simplicitie, and prayse God almyghty.</title>
            <title>Omnium gentium mores. Book 1. English</title>
            <author>Joannes, ca. 1485-1535.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1554</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3196.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13062</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13062)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 236:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discription of the contrey of Aphrique the fyrst part of the worlde, with the cituation of al the countreys together, with the perticuler maners lawes, and ceremonies, of dyuers people inhabityng in the same part. Translated out of Frenche into Englyshe by Wyllyam Prat of London, the fyrst daye of the newe yere, M.CCCCC.LIIII. Rede it dylygently, marke it perfectly, reuolue it thorowly, beare it equally, beholde the auctours simplicitie, and prayse God almyghty.</title>
                  <title>Omnium gentium mores. Book 1. English</title>
                  <author>Joannes, ca. 1485-1535.</author>
                  <author>Prat, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[174] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the signe of the George next to saynt Dunstones Churche by Wyllyam Powel],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[f1554]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of book 1 of Boemus, Johannes.  Omnium gentium mores.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 191.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 191 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L (-L8).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaf K8 poorly filmed.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Africa --  Religious life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRIPTION OF THE CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TREY OF APHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>QVE.</p>
            <p>the fyrſt part of the worlde, with the cituation of al the countreys to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, with the perticuler maners lawes, and ceremonies, of dyuers people inhabityng in the ſame part. Tranſlated out of Frenche into Englyſhe by Wyllyam Prat of London, the fyrſt daye of the newe yere, M.CCCCC.L.IIII.</p>
            <p>Rede it dylygently, Marke it perfectly, Reuolue it thorowly, Beare it equally, Beholde the auctours ſimplicitie, And prayſe God almyghty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable lord Edwarde Courtney Earle of Deuonſhyre, his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruant Wyllyam Pratte wyſheth hym peace, grace, &amp; mercy from our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſt. Amen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or want of a coſtly and precious Iewel, haue here offered to you this baſe gyfte: The diſcriptyon of Aphrique (my good lorde) though not ſo good as is wylled, nor ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent as is wyſhed. Yet mooſte humbly beſechynge you to take it in good parte. It is ſayd the minde of gyftes is beſt: For in the gyftes of frendes, the value of the thinges whiche be preſented, be not to be conſidred, but the good wyl of the preſenter. That worthy Kynge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:3"/>
Xerxes receyued thanfully of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne ſtranger a handful of water, And Chryſt alſo accepted the wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes two farthynges, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred theym before other greate and ryche offeringes: So I truſt you wyll this my rude and homely preſent, and wey in an equal peyre of balans my good wyl towardes your Lordeſhyp, for to my power I haue done, and as farre as my capacytie wolde reache, as well in the tranſlation as other wayes, I haue wrytten, <hi>In magnis et volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe ſat eſt.</hi> In greater thynges whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che might paſſe my ſimple capacitie it is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me to haue willed, wyl otherwhiles eſpecially in thoſe thinges which might paſſe a mans power, doth merite comendacions although his enterpriſe take no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. To my purpoſe. Now ſeynge that the end or extinct of my longe
<pb facs="tcp:13062:3"/>
wyſhe is fynyſhed, I can not but hyghly laude God therfore, ſo ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is your Lordeſhyps proſperus ſucceſſe vnto me, as the fortunate hour is of the traueling woman in the delyuerance of her chyld, your longe aduerſitie was not ſo lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table, but your proſperitie is as ioyful. Trulye as often as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende and wey with my ſelfe the depnes of your aduerſities cauſeth me to wonder, conſyderynge how that you haue ben toſſed in the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues of the ſea, in ſtormes, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſts, and in extreme peryls, yea, amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt (if I myght ſo ſay) deuouring Lions, and yet to ſe how god hath preſerued your good Lordeſhippe: what may I ſay. ſhal I aſcrybe it to dame Fortune, as the poites did in olde time, and render vp thankes to her? No certeinly, I ſhal thanke the myghty Lorde aboue, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer
<pb facs="tcp:13062:4"/>
of his electe. I do fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade with my ſelfe that god hath choſen you, and preſerued you, to the ende that you ſhulde be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, (when it ſhall pleaſe oure ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Quene to call you) a worthy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celler, a preſeruer of the publike weale, &amp; a fortherer of her good &amp; godli laws: for god hath endowed you with a mooſte precious gyfte, and hath gyuen you a great talent and wel worthy. For that you day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly augment and encreaſe it. Howe can a man but wonder (thoughe that the giftes of God be not to be marueiled at) as often as he ſhal conceaue with hym ſelfe the courſe of your lyfe togethers, with your education. I meane your longe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, in ſuche a deſert place, where in a maner neyther ſiuilitie, nor wyſedome was to be learned, yet to beholde your ſtate and ſtudy
<pb facs="tcp:13062:4"/>
howe that you haue applied youre mynde to good letters, as well to the Romains as to the french, Ita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion, and Spanyſh beſides al theſe I can not ſo eaſely expreſſe as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the nomber of other vertues and qualyties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which raine in you, what condinge prayſe dothe that chylde deſerue, which with out a nourſe doth fede him ſelfe with the ſwete pappe of learnynge? Euen ſo howe much is your Lordſhip wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy of lawde, who without tutors but of and by your owne induſtry and labour, haue atteyned to this perfection of learnynge, what preg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant wyt is this, it is eaſely deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, howe well you haue folowed the peynters lyne, here may we ſe <hi>nulla preterit ſine linea dies</hi> ſo haue you let no day eſcape without dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge of a profitable lyne, as you haue begon ſo procede, and euery day drawe a lyne to the profyte of
<pb facs="tcp:13062:5"/>
your good lady and quene aduaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cement of her honour, and the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon weales, ſo in ſtudyeng, with god you ſhall be reteyned, and of the people beloued. For yf the late offenders had beſtowed their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and emploied their knowlege to the ſeruice of theyr Quene and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres, God wolde haue proſpered them, but ſeynge they dyd contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he ſhortened not onely theyr moſt nequitious and wycked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but alſo punyſſhed ſome of theym accordyng to theyr deſertes. Truely it was a Goodely myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and glaſſe, for all nobles to loke in, exhortyng your Lordeſhip to beholde both theyr beginnynge and theyr endes. what was the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the countrey of <hi>Caria,</hi> which once was ſuche a plentyfull contrey as ours hath ben and wyl be ageyne, nowe we haue ſo ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous
<pb facs="tcp:13062:5"/>
a quene, and noble councel, who ſtudyeth dayly and trauaileth hourly to bryng in plenty, but only the lybertie of a multytude? This vnlawfull lybertie is called <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie,</hi> a myſchyefe truly as euyll as any tyranny, I wold al men wold haue in remembraunce this godly ſayeng, <hi>Noſce te ipſum,</hi> Plato diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crybeth this diuyne ſentens to god Appollo, but truly I wyll diſcribe it to all men, and wolde councel the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lay the feare of God before their eyes, to remember their beginning, theyr byrth preſent ſtate, and end, So wolde I wiſhe that your lord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppe wolde beare in memorye, your former aduerſities with the goodnes of God exte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon you, in delyuerynge you out of the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of all your enemyes, haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the poore, gyue attentyue eare to theyr peticions, feade them
<pb facs="tcp:13062:6"/>
which honger, and gyue theym to drynke which thyrſt, and cheryſhe your poore ſeruantes, for to what prayſe with god, loue with the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, honour to the renome doth the noble man ateyne to? which in time of his auctoritie and lyfe preferreth and aduaunceth his pore ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, <hi>percontra</hi> in how much diſplea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure with God, hate with people, diſtruction of his honour, and into other infinit dangers doth he incur in whoſe ſeruyce his poore ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes do not floryſhe but decay. I cannot but lament ſo often as I call to memory the lamentacions of dyuers of the late dukes ſeruantes the which (as they ſayd) be vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li brought to ruine and extreme po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertie by ſeruynge of him, wheras they truſted to haue floryſhed, yea ſome of them curſyng him, and wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that they had neuer ſeene his
<pb facs="tcp:13062:6"/>
head. Alas alas what ouerſyght was it, when that in his chyfe and freſhe dignitie he myght haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced them whiche toke peynes and ſpent theyr ſubſtans to do him honour. Truly eyther couetouſnes ſurmounted him, or els vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge fayled him. We haue one worthy Byſhoppe in this realme, which hath purchaſed him ſelfe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petuall honour and prayſe, as well for his conuenient hoſpitalitie, as for preferrynge of his ſeruauntes, whoſe doyenge be notable, a clere myrrour for all the reſte of nobles to beholde, truſtyng your lordſhip wyl folow his ſteppes, and lay his actes before your eyes as a glaſſe to loke in, ſo in doenge, I knowe god wyl (as he hath al redy) cauſe the people to loue you, gyue you long lyfe: with proſperous ſucceſſe and your fatall ende honorable. I
<pb facs="tcp:13062:7"/>
ſhall not neade (my good Lorde) to be tedious in reherſing of many of theſe exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, for that I know your ſinguler wyſdome hath attei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a farder knowledge of them then I am able to declare or ſhew, but to the entente that other maye therby be admoniſhed, ſo by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell may folowe the ſteppes which leade them to vertue and goodnes. I haue enterpriſed (honorable lord to tranſlate into Englyſhe <hi>Aphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, Aſie.</hi> and <hi>Europia,</hi> the .iii. parts of the worlde, and for aſmuche as the hole volume is great, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng ſmal tyme, and leyſure gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me, wolde be loth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng this fyrſt part ſhulde be hindred in the impreſſion, thought it good not onely to dedicate this to your Lordſhyp, but alſo for the fruite I perceaue in the hole worke to thende that the reader ſhulde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb facs="tcp:13062:7"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſidue, haue therfore both ſet forth the hole table &amp; a prologe, truſtynge that he wyll couet the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two partes. And bycauſe I owe to my lorde of Darbie for his many and manyfold pleſures done for me, a great ſome, I pretend in one part of payment to preſente to him the diſcription of <hi>Aſie,</hi> or <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> the ſeconde parte, beynge alſo greatly in daunger to my good mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres Clarentius for her ſondrye trauayles for me, haue appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the laſt part of Europia to her myſtreſhip. Theſe two laſte with expedicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wyl endeuour my ſelfe to end In the meane ſeaſon, I ſhal moſt humbly beſeche your Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp to accept this in good worthe and the faultes therein, do impute to ignorans, partely for want of tyme, beſydes al this to conſyder my pore eſtate, longe tyme abſent
<pb facs="tcp:13062:8"/>
abſent from my ſtudies, and the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginnyng of my enterpryſes, being the firſt that euer I tranſlated out of the frenche tonge, and to my ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (the obſcuritie of the ſentences conſidred) neyther is the tranſlation out of latin, Italion, or Spanyſhe, ſo difficile and hard, as the tranſlation of french into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe. To conclude in token of a Newyeres gyft I do here exhibit vnto your Lordſhip this diſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Aphrique. A gyft I graunt not ſo gret as is owed, nor ſo good as is wyſhed, (as before I ſayde) yet where office and loue oweth much and wyll wolde paye all, thoughe power drawethe backe not able to diſcharge either loues dette, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite all that wyll wolde, yet by the vewe of any reaſonable iudge the yelde of thone, and the bente of thother, ought with the creditour
<pb facs="tcp:13062:8"/>
to ſupply the thyrdes defect.</p>
            <p>The cauſe occurrynge lyke in me, be it lawfull to vſe ſuch a ſhyft, not onely to excuſe my ſmall habilitie exhibytynge ſo ſmall tribute of ſo much as is owed and wylled, but alſo to grate at your Lordeſhyps handes, notwithſtandynge accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion therof as of a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numente of loues dette, and token of wylles wyſhe, how ſo euer malyngne power ſhall temper the ſame in the vtteraune<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Thus I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende your Lorde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppe to God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:9"/>
            <head>The prologue to the Readar.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auynge had oportu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie and tyme graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted me, haue beſtow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the houres of ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in accumulating the faſſyons mooſte worthy of memory together with the pertyculer obſeruacyons and lawes of dyuerſe people, in ſorte that the fathers of hyſtories, hath moſt amplie writen of. As <hi>Herodo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, Diodore. Sicilien, Beroſe, Stra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bo, Solin, Troge, Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peie, Ptolomie, Pline, Cornele Tacite, De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis, Aphri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>queni, Pompenemele, Caeſar, Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe,</hi> and of the auctours in our age and tyme, as <hi>Vincent Aeneas Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utus,</hi> which ſins had the name of pope Pie the ſeconde, <hi>Antonie Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellique, Iohn Nanclere, Ambros Capelin,</hi> and <hi>Nicolas Perot,</hi> in their
<pb facs="tcp:13062:9"/>
cornucopies, and manye other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Auctours. I haue made a lyttle abridgement or abſtract, not in hope of any lucour or particuler profite, but prouoked to do this, onely do require fauour of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: hauynge had the true and free leyſure, to imploye togethers with the fruitefull ioye and delectacion whiche I haue noted in the whole worke by me encerpriſed. And yf thou wylt vnderſtand (O gentyl re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) the hiſtories, and be deſirus of the knowledge of them whiche I haue gathered together, aſwell the newe and freſh, as alſo the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient examples both good and euil ſeruynge to this purpoſe, to the ende that they maye preſente vnto the thinges vertuous and of honor as euill and vitious, thou mayſte folowe thoſe thynges which leade to vertue, and require diſcretion to
<pb facs="tcp:13062:10"/>
ſhonne that which doth entende to reproche and fylthynes, therein thou ſhalt ſe the magnificens and felicitie of the mortall men now ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge, and alſo the poore and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple lyfe of them whiche came fyrſte vpon yearch, ſyns the creacion of man vntyl the flud of Noe. Againe mani other worlds after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid flud In ſomuch the humaine creatures were diſparced thorowe the hole earth, and lyued without doynge any traficke or marchaundyſe one with an other, or vſynge of money currant from man to man, in ſorte that they coulde not exell one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in good dedes. All thynges were equally deuyded amongeſt them, that they had neither more nor leſſe then the heuens, the earth, together with the waters commen ſo that they were not couetous of any honoure or ryches, hauynge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:10"/>
that, contented them ſelues, to paſe theyr lyfe in playne fielde, vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, or vnder the ſhadow of ſome tree, or coueryng of an houſe, with one or many women and the whole lynage, without al feare and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, onely contentyng them ſelues with the thinges, which the earth brought forth, with the mylke of the beaſtes, and for theyr drynke water ſufficed. Fyrſt for theyr ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel toke the large leaues of trees but a lyttel after, the world began to inuent the wayes to cloth theim with the ſkinnes of beſtes, one lyke vnto the other. Man created was ſo lyttle carefull to be in ſuertye, that he did not paſſe or deſyre to be loked vp in walled Cities, or in for treſes, made with ſtronge rampers but wandred and ſtrayed abrode lyke other beaſtes, and had no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine place to take his reſt, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:11"/>
in the fielde reſted hym. To whom when that the night appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, was in greate tranquylytie without feare of theues or robbers yet at the laſt beinge compelled to do the contrary by ſuch lyke chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by ſucceſſion of tyme that the worlde might encreaſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye, whiche the enuey and dyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of their wiles was the cauſe of the varietie, and chaunge of the hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayne inclinations, agayne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the induſtry and labour of man the fruites whiche came from the earth, was not ſufficient to noriſhe them, that lyued then, prouoked them to exercyſe one with an other and by the aboue ſayde Calamyties they were ſo greatly weryed with trauayles that they folowed the coures of wylde beaſtes, wherfore the humayne creatures by lyttle &amp; lyttle accompanyenge togethers,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:11"/>
conſultede, by a commen ſeecours and ayde to expulſe ſuch euyl cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and hurtes, beganne to prepare and appoint to eueryone of theym certeine portions of grounde, vpon the which they buylded lyttle hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and made perticions of theyr landes by certeyne limittes, in ſo much that by little and lyttle, they made dyches and walles, and at the laſt there was appoynted a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeir eſtate or common weal. In lykewyſe they eſtabliſhed certeine lawes and mageſtrates, by whome euery man ſhulde be ruled. In ſo muche at the laſt there was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a greate concorde and peace amongeſt ſo great a multytude of people. Sins that tyme men inuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to lyue not onely by the fruites and noriture which the erth hir ſelf brought forth, and that the beaſtes or cattell gaue, but alſo by their
<pb facs="tcp:13062:12"/>
manye and ſundry induſtries and labours by theym excogitated, and founde out the maner to make the ſhippes to ryde vpon the ſeas, ſome to ſerue for marchaundyſe, other ſome to abyde the countreys. Alſo ſome inuented the cartes with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to drawe theym, and after that they began to haue courſe gold and ſyluer, then was the aparel of men more ſumptuous, theyr language adorned with eloquens, theyr fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentacion more ſiuile, theyr diete more delicate, their building more larger and gorgious, in fyne the morrall creatures in continuaunce of tyme, were altred and chaunged as well from theyr condicions, as from theyr barbarouſnes and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elnes, they became humayne, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyl, and gracious, that at the laſte they ruled them ſelues ſo diſcretely that they them ſelues banyſhed all
<pb facs="tcp:13062:12"/>
their inhumanitie, and vnciuilitie as to kyll one an other, to eate the fleſhe of men, and to occupye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the firſt they mete without diſcrecion or regarde of blud or kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, with ſuch lyke vices and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections. After they had taſted of this euyll order, and atteyne to more reſon by theyr trauaile, made the earth fruteful, the which before was hydden ouer as a wylde foreſt, vnhabited and mooſt vnprofitable for man. They remoued away the great ſtones and ſtubbes of trees, made the fayre waters &amp; ſprynges to be ſought for, in the marſhe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This they did and all to make it plaine, and to cauſe it loſe his old and auncient forme, wheras before it was hilly and rude. In ſo vſyng the earth, at the laſt brought forth wynes and other encreaſe aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, the whiche before did yelde
<pb facs="tcp:13062:13"/>
them but a lyttle quantitie of wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges &amp; crabs. Moreouer by the infinite gardens &amp; arbors, whiche they did ſet rounde about the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains &amp; ſpringes, made the valeys freſhe, and leſte the hyghe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, becauſe of the wodes and foreſtes, and after knewe howe to order the grounde to brynge forth fruite. Ageyne theyr places where they inhabited at the firſt were lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but hauyng dwelt there a time from ſmale vyllages became great Cyties. vpon the hygh mountaines they buylded townes and ſtronge caſtels, &amp; in the valeyes great tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and churches, to the ende that the fountaines might be more hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſommer and delectable. they were richli made of faire cut marbelſtone and they ſet trees al about to giue them a pleaſaunt ſhadowe. And more frome the ſayde welles they
<pb facs="tcp:13062:13"/>
cauſed waters by the pipes to deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende and come into theyr Cyties They made hauens &amp; crekes in the ſea to harbor the ſhips. They alſo made many ryght places, into the whiche the ſhyppes myght retyre backe without daunger of windes and tempeſtes At the end they had ſo appoyncted al thynges as well in the ſea, as in the lande, which yf we do conſider the ſtate preſent and after what it was afore tyme, a man wolde take it to be a countrey aboue all other, then that whiche was fyrſt created, and wold iudge it more lyke the gardeyne or para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe out of the whiche oure forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Adam and Eue was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en for the tranſgreſſion of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly commaundement then other wyſe. Moreouer the people inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many artes and ſciences moſte wyttye (as letters and tables to
<pb facs="tcp:13062:14"/>
wryte which after was had in vſe, they be oftentimes exempted from the condicion of the mortalles in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng memory of them to theyr po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie which made participacions of theyr inuentions, and by this, me thynketh that the mortall men myght be ſoner called ſome earthly gods then men, had it not ben for that malygne Sathan, which hath by a moſt peſtilente ſeade ſowen in the worlde, brought confuſion: for he ſeynge that the humayne crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures dyd encreaſe, and that the condicion of theyr lyfe paſſed from good to better, beynge ſtyrred vp by an enuy hath brought thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into bondage, by reaſon of theyr ſondry and manye ſins and inormities com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted. And ſins the true lyght ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, there came in Idolaters whiche woulde haue darkened the ſame. There engendred many ſects
<pb facs="tcp:13062:14"/>
amongeſt the people. To proue this trewe, we do ſe that at theſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, thoſe of <hi>Aſie, Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, Perſe, Cyrie, aſyre, Medie</hi> and in <hi>Aphrique</hi> Thoſe of Egipte, of <hi>Numidie, Libie, Maritanie,</hi> and in <hi>Europia.</hi> thoſe of <hi>Grece, Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne,</hi> and all other whiche be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obedience of the Turke, do obſerue duly for the moſt part the lawes of wycked mahoment, and his falſe doctrine, and madde, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakynge our ſauiour Chryſte. The people of <hi>Scythie,</hi> of whome there is a greate nomber, and be nowe called <hi>Tartariens</hi> or <hi>Tartares.</hi> doo worſhhyp moſte commonly the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles of the Emperoure Cham, ſome do worſhyp the ſtarres, not withſtandynge there be which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute honoure to the onely God, and vſe the epiſtles and doctrine of ſaynct Paule. The Indes which
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:15"/>
vnder Preſt Iohn, do folowe the true Chriſten religion, (Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe) there is dyuerſitie betwene their doynges and oures. At theſe preſentes, there be no nacions whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che do obſerue the Catholyke faith but the Englyſhe men, the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, Italyons, Spanyardes, Frenchemen, Scottes, Iryſhmen, the Danes, Liuones Pruſſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Polland, of Hongery, and thoſe in the Ilondes, thoſe of the Rodes, of Cecilie, of Corſe, of Sardayne, and ſome other regions. That cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el enemie of mankinde, hath ſo ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him ſelfe that by the dyuerſitie of religion and ceremonies, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aboueſayde natyons had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulerly choſen and meinteined to be the trewe waies to bring to eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nal bleſſe and felicitie, in reputynge al other falſe and Eronious, euery
<pb facs="tcp:13062:15"/>
one after their own faſhcions with all their endeuoyr dyd ſet for them moſt ample maner their owne reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, wherevppon hathe folowed ſuch hate, amongeſt men that they which haue taken great iourneyes into far contreys haue not gone in ſaue garde. In ſo much the men the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues haue ſtopped, the paſſage to come to the perfecte knowledge of dyuers nations, whiche doth make me iudge that manye there be that beleue all that is wrytten of oure purpoſe to be but fables, for that they haue not ſkant the knowledge of the people and nacions which be nygh to them. I meane they know not theyr owne neyghboures, as thoſe regio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſituated next to theirs and all is for not hauynge trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. We do ſe that the knowledge of theſe thinges hath ben ſo agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pleaſaunt to many, that it
<pb facs="tcp:13062:16"/>
hath redowned to theyr greate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour glory and profyte. As it is moſte certeyne, that many hath not refuſed to theyr ende to atteyne to this knowledge leaft theyr natyue contreys, theyr fathers, mothers, wyfe, chyldren, and frendes, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardinge (the which is more) their helth and ſalut, to put them ſelues in infinit dangers, &amp; contempnynge all thynges whiche moue them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr enterpryſes. yea, and to their peyne haue taken vppon theym the longe and dangerous vyage by ſea whereby (as I knowe) not on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly but this tyme preſent, but alſo in tyme paſte, in a maner ſins the worlde began, moſt comonly they haue ben in great credit, auctoritie and reputacion, and made gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of publyke weales, and gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to be councellers, Iudges, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13062:16"/>
greate capyteynes or chyefe of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and all by the experiens of many people, with maner of theyr vſages and lyuinges, and longe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages in contreis. Other hath attei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to ſo great knowledge, that of the great nombre of their diſciples were inſtructed diuers be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the Phyloſophers, lyke as of Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes were called Socrateques, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which were the diſciple of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> were nominated <hi>achademiques</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Ariſtotel, Peripathetiques</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Antiſthenes, Ciniques,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> were called <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaiques,</hi> of <hi>Zenon, Stoiques,</hi> of <hi>Pythagoras, Pithagoriques.</hi> And if we loke a lyttle nyer, we ſhal finde that they which haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much auctoritie to the auncient lawers, as to <hi>Minos,</hi> and <hi>Rhadamantus,</hi> to wardes them of <hi>Crete. Orpheus,</hi> to them of <hi>Thrace, Draco,</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:17"/>
to the <hi>Athiens. Licurgus,</hi> to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedemoniens,</hi> Moyſes to the Iues and dyuers towardes other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that euery one of them might be inſtructed, and to inſtytute cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne religion and lawes. Yf theſe men had kept theyr owne contreys this had not ben, but bycauſe they conſumed theyr age in other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys they were able to inſtructe, hauyng afterward the ſame know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Caldes, Mages, Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes Gimnoſophiſtes,</hi> &amp; the preſts of Egypte whiche were all men of great knowledge, and of a moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent naturall wit, with whome they hadde frequented a certeyne ſpace and tyme. we do alſo fynde that this knowledge hath greatly ſerued the excellent perſonages and princes in the olde tyme, as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of <hi>Crete,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poet wryteth dyd meet the Circuite of the world
<pb facs="tcp:13062:17"/>
fyue tymes. To his two chyldren, as to <hi>Dioniſos,</hi> otherwyſe called <hi>Bacchus,</hi> &amp; to <hi>Hercules</hi> the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, with his immitatour <hi>Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns Iaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> with all his bende. To <hi>Vliſſes</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che inuaded ſo much the daungers of the ſea, and to <hi>Aeneas,</hi> of Troy, to <hi>Titus Darius, Xerxes, Alexander</hi> the great, <hi>Hanibal Metridatis,</hi> king of <hi>Pont,</hi> which coulde ſpeke fyftye languages, of the fyfty Realmes whiche was vnder him. The innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable nobles of Rome, as to the two <hi>Scipions,</hi> to <hi>Marius Le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tulus Pompeie</hi> the great, <hi>Iulius Ceſar, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauian auguſt.</hi> To the <hi>Conſtantines Charles, Otheons, Courades. Henryz Federiz,</hi> and that in theyr actes of warres, by the whiche they haue purchaſed to theym ſelues eternall glory and prayſe. Seynge then the knowledge of dyuers nations, is
<pb facs="tcp:13062:18"/>
greately to be delited in and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, I ſhal deſyre the (gentyl rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to put to thy good wyll, and reade ouer the thynges conteyned in this boke, for to this purpoſe the ſame be gathered together, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the aſwell to a perfection of knowledge bothe of the countreys and the nature of eche people, as if I ſhuld leade the by the hand from one place to an other from one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to an other, or to poynte the with my finger. I haue manifeſted to me the maner of the lyuinge as well of the auncient, as of freſhe memory, together with the citua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of al countreys, and how they were inhabited in olde tyme, and be nowe preſent. And be not offended with me (gentyll reader) for want of auſteritie. In that I haue not holly ſatiſfied thy appetite as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
<pb facs="tcp:13062:18"/>
thou deſyreſt, I haue done it rather to chalenge vnto my ſelfe rebuke and ſhame, then praiſe, yet I haue wrytten neyther of the thynges paſſed, nor preſente, but they haue ben more then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande tymes ſpoken of, in the ſame termes, in hundreth of auctours, I wold not thou ſhuldeſt thinke that I do attrybute all this worke or inuention to my owne doynge, and to haue it ſet forth for any newal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to ſatiſfie ſome perticuler man. I ſhal hartly deſyre the (gentyl rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der) vnderſtande of me, that I do entreate of many thynges worthy of knowledge, parte came of my ſelfe, and parte alſo of the treaſure of my bookes, and as the good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a famylie (to whom our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chryſt hath compared al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that profeſſe the faith) to his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:19"/>
ſo iudge of me that theſe whiche I heare preſente, be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient thynges, &amp; come from ſtrange auctours. I require the beare me good wyll, and take all thynges in good part, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng God to meinteyne the in proſperitie, which I beſeche hym hertely to graunt. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:19"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>THE TREVVE OPINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the diuine wryters tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the Original of Man. The fyrſt Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the diuine</hi> maieſtie of God had finiſhed the creation of the heauens, and vniuerſal frame the whiche for his ornament and moſt comely compoſicion, was called <hi>Mundus,</hi> together with al thynges conteyned in the Cyrcuite of the ſame at the fyfthe day of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. vpon the ſyxt daye the mooſte noble creature called Man was made, for to be lord ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges aboue mencioned, Leauyng to him the vſe and pleaſures of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Of al other creatures, he was only endued with celeſtiall wyſedome, and had the name of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyuen vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:20"/>
becauſe he was made of a veyne of red earth. A whyle after was gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to him a company keper, to the entente that ſolitarines ſhulde not anoy him. The woman which was made of his rybbe. They were ſet in the mooſt delectable place of the worlde, beynge compaſſed with fayre ryuers, that place was reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with yonge ſprynges, trees, herbes, and flowers, wonderfull pleaſaunt and delectable to behold, and for that cauſe it was called Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radyſe by a greeke terme. Theſe two perſons for a ſpace led a moſt happy lyfe, and without feelynge of yll, for the earthe of her ſelfe brought forth al fruites at deſyre. Notwithſtandynge, for breaking the commaundementes of God, they were dryuen to forſake that place, after that the earth was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:20"/>
whereby ſhe brought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge forth accordynge to her for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer fertillitie. They were conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to ſeke theyr lyuyng with ſwet and laboure, then raygned all kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſyckeneſſe, felynge of colde and heate vppon the humayne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, Cain was the fyrſt begotten chylde of theim, and Abel was the ſecond, and after them many more, and ſo encreaſed the world and the earth was well inhabyted. The more the nomber of men multiplied the more did they encreaſe in vyce, and theyr lyuynge dyd dayly waxe from il to worſe. In ſteade of good doinge to theyr neyghbours, they began to annoy and hurt one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in ſteade of acknowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge of the creatour, they had in contempte the goodnes of God, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that tyme continued and encreaſed
<pb facs="tcp:13062:21"/>
the wyckednes of men, in ſuch ſort that God therefore after he hadde found one iuſt man which was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Noe, for whoſe cauſe he ſaued all his famyly for the reſtorynge of mankynde, ſent the fludde, whiche drowned the hole earth with al ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge thynges therevpon, excepte thoſe which were ſaued in the holy arke made by the ſayde Noe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> church</note> fyue monethes then after the beginning of the flud, the arke touched grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon the mountaynes, of <hi>Armenie,</hi> and Noe went out with his, and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>creaſed mankynde in ſhort ſpace af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the helpe of God, he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed to haue all the partes of the earth inhabyted, and for that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſente his chyldren into dyuerſe contreys in the world, he ſent his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Cain</hi> into <hi>Egipt</hi> with his dukes (as <hi>Beroſe</hi> reciteth) <hi>Eſennius</hi> into <hi>Libie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:21"/>
&amp; in <hi>Cerene Tritames:</hi> &amp; al the reſt of <hi>Aphrique,</hi> he ſent <hi>Iapetus</hi> the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp; <hi>Atalas.</hi> Into the <hi>Orie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal Aſie</hi> he ſente <hi>Ganges,</hi> with ſome of the chyldren of <hi>Gomer</hi> the <hi>Gallica,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the luckye <hi>Arabie,</hi> he ſent <hi>Sabus</hi> the Encenſe bearer, <hi>Ara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> was by him appointed chyefe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerte <hi>Arabie,</hi> and <hi>Petretus</hi> capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne of <hi>Araby</hi> the ſtony, he cauſed the contrey from <hi>Damas</hi> vnto the borders of <hi>Paleſtyne</hi> to be inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byted by <hi>Canaan.</hi> Into <hi>Europia</hi> he ſent <hi>Tuiſco</hi> the gyaunt to be kynge of <hi>Sarmatie,</hi> from the ryuer of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nais</hi> vnto the ryuer of <hi>Rh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> nyhg vnto the ſame <hi>Tuiſco,</hi> there dydde inhabite the chyldren of <hi>Iſter,</hi> and <hi>Meſa</hi> with his brethren, who had the contrey from the mount <hi>Adule</hi> vnto <hi>Meſemberie,</hi> and the contrey of <hi>Ponticque</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:22"/>
at that tyme <hi>Tyras, Achardius,</hi> and <hi>Emathius,</hi> helde <hi>Italy, Gomer</hi> the Frenche man, <hi>Samotes</hi> the <hi>Celtes,</hi> the whiche be the countreys of the ſayde <hi>Gaule,</hi> nowe called Fraunce, and <hi>Iubal</hi> enioyed the <hi>Celriberiens</hi> which is Spayne. The ſodayne and ſhort departure from his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (who had not yet learned ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the lyuyng ne maners of their parentes) was the cauſe of al the dyuerſitie that ſyns folowed. In ſo muche that <hi>Cham</hi> (who dyd flee for the ſhame done to his father,) remayned he, his wyfe, and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in thoſe partes of <hi>Arabie,</hi> &amp; ſynce called by his name <hi>Cain,</hi> who neuer gaue to his poſteritie any preceptes of religion, in ſo muche that he trauailed not to learne any. where vpon it came to paſſe by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of tyme, the one ſente after
<pb facs="tcp:13062:22"/>
the other out of one lande to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byte an other. After hauynge oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys in the world for this ſkattered lygnage multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed meruelouſly, fynally they fel into moſt execrable errours, out of the whiche they colde not vnwrap themſelues, theyr language chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and it was not to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande or intelligeble, the trew worſhyppynge and knowledgynge of God was out of remembrance. So men haue lyued after ſuche a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſort that one can not wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerne the lyuing betwene the beſts and them. They whiche do paſſe Egipt for the admiracion they had of the celeſtiall creatures, beganne to worſhyp as gods the ſonne, and the mone, callynge the ſon <hi>Oſyris,</hi> and the moone <hi>Iſis.</hi> They attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted godlynes to reſpiracion, by the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:23"/>
whiche all men do lyue, vnder the name of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> to the element of fyre, vnder the name of <hi>Vulcaine,</hi> to the ayre, vnder the name of <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> to the earth, vnder the name of <hi>Seres,</hi> and to dyuers other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, vnder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> many other names. And they of <hi>Egypt</hi> do not onely thus walke in darkenes, but alſo in the countreys poſſeſſed by them, whiche be deſcended from <hi>Cham,</hi> haue ben ſubiett to execrable bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and ignorance of the trew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Moreouer there was neuer countrey that the people were ſo fertyll to brynge forthe chyldren, nor better merytynge the name of a mother for this reſpect, then this part of <hi>Arabie,</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> with his occupied. Suche and ſo greate a ruyne was brought to man kynde, the banyeſh mente of
<pb facs="tcp:13062:23"/>
that onely perſonage, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> and <hi>Iaphet,</hi> with all theyr ſtocke, who were inſtituted &amp; appoynted by theyr fathers in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne lawe, were contented with ſmall poſſeſſions, and therfore they were not ſo largely diſparſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe out the hole worlde as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Then it came to paſſe, that the loue of the truth (that is to ſay the true hollynes and adoration of the ryght God) dyd remayne hyd in one onely nacion, vntyll the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge of <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>he falſe opinion of the Etheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques and Infydels, touchynge the Originall of man. Chapi, ii.</head>
            <p>THe Phyloſophers in tyme paſt without any knowledge of the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:24"/>
trewe Godde, of longe tyme dyd ſpeake of naturall thynges. Some of them beleaued that the worlde was a thynge not created, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptyble, and that mankynde was without takynge beginning. The other ageyne iudged, that the worlde was created and ſubiecte to corruption, and that men were created by ſucceſſion of tyme. To confyrme this opinion they ſayde, before any thynge had his begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, heauen and earthe had one onely forme, and that the propriete of theſe two thinges was confuſe that ſynce theſe two elementes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated one from the other wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſuche diſpoſition and forme of the worlde, that we perceyue the eyre in contynuall agitacion, and that of him, the part of the fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er had gotten the hygheſt place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13062:24"/>
of his agilitie and lyghtnes, and that by this reaſon, the ſonne and the other ſtarres, hadde kepte theyr places and certeyne courſes, in the hyghe region, as for that which reſteth beynge as of a moiſt qualitie moued but a lyttle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyrſt place, becauſe of his heuynes and weyght, hauynge a kynde of moyſtenes in hym of the moyſteſt part one wold ſay that the ſea had folowed it, and that the heauynes diſapoynted of ſo greate humydite ſhall retourne to ſlammy earth and ſoft, the whiche by lyttle and lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſhall harden, by reaſon of the heate of the ſonne. In ſuch ſort the aboueſayde by the vyolence of the heat ſhal be ſwollen &amp; ryſen, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon many humours vnder the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lones of the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, riſen vp, were gethered, and by lyttle and lyttle
<pb facs="tcp:13062:25"/>
conuerted and tourned to matters rotten, as we ſe hathe happened in the maryſhes of Egypt. Ageyne the earth beynge colde and moyſte of her nature, is made hote in a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpace by the vehemente heate of the ayre, that a man wolde iudge in a ſmall tyme, that the heate had ben mingled with moyſt thynges, whiche agayne ſhalbe formed in a proper matter, and engendred to an efficacie, to the whiche was gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen moyſtues, ſhed by nyght and by the vygneur of the ſonne hadde kept and noryſhed this matter ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratyue vntyll that by contynua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce of tyme, the aboueſayd mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters ſhalbe compelled to aſcend vp alſo, as yf the tyme had ben come, that the ſayde hardeneſſe woulde haue rendred that whiche it hathe engendred, that maye be open and
<pb facs="tcp:13062:25"/>
broken by the vehemency of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in a lyttle ſpace after, brought forthe all kynde of beaſtes, of the which, thoſe whiche were pertici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of the greate heate, were vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latyfe or made to fly, and did win the hygheſt region of the eyre. The other which had more of the weigh tines or ponderouſnes of the earth were made to remayne creapynge, and ſome goyng vpon the ground. The other which helde them ſelues of the qualitie of water, were tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the element of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and toke the name Fyſhe, and by this the earth partly becauſe of the heate of the ſon, partly becauſe of the wyndes, became more dryer and warmer, ſo that the myghtye beaſtes ceaſed engendrynge, but they which engendred by a mutual coniunction did bringe forth other.
<pb facs="tcp:13062:26"/>
They ſay after this ſort, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were fyrſt created, who hath euer ſynce ſought theyr meate and lyuynge in the fieldes, &amp; feade after a ſtrange and wylde ſort, eatynge nothynge but herbes, and the fruite of the trees, and dyd no labour, for what by occaſyon of the hurte that the wylde beaſtes dyd theym before, and for feare they ſhoulde dayly, they gathered theym ſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for theyr commen vtillitie and profyte that they myght ſuccoure one an other, and prepare places to dwell in. Ageyne for that the ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of theyr mouthes were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſe, they eſtudied to frame theyr tongues to a certeyne ſpeache, ſo that by lyttle and lyttle they gaue euery thyng a name. And becauſe they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded into dyuers partes, and regi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of the worlde, they formed
<pb facs="tcp:13062:26"/>
dyuerſe and diuerſitie of language and conſequentely a ferme in theyr letters. And by this the humayne creatures lyuynge in great pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and without vnderſtandynge how to make reſeruacion for their neceſſities, with that whiche God ſent theim, as the fruite whiche the earth brought forth, fortuned oftentimes that one (amongeſt the greate nomber) dyed for hunger, and ſome for colde, wherevpon me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtructed by experience was dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and learned to prepare a buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to defende them from theſe and ſuch lyke inconuenientes, ſerched (as ſaith the Philoſophers) caues to auoyde the vyolence of the cold and reſerued the frut for theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſion afterwarde they had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the proprietie of fyre, whae it was, together with all other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries.
<pb facs="tcp:13062:27"/>
In a ſpace after, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented al thynges apt and mete for humayne lyfe. To conclude neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie was the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peller to ſeake theſe inuentions, at the laſt man hadde the arte to vſe one an other in his place, that the handes, the wordes the excellencie of the ſpirites, was helpers togethers, and ſerued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſ be they which be perſwaded that the originall of man is, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue rehearſed, and haue not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred it to the dyuyne prouidence of God, doth hold opinion that the <hi>Ethiopie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> were the fyrſt that were procreated amongeſt the mortalles and had this opinion, for that the lande of <hi>Ethiopie</hi> is the neighbour to the ſonne, as before al other to feale the heate, howe muche as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they did, neyther more nor leſſe then al the reſt of the earth, the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:13062:27"/>
earth was ſlymye, then it ſhoulde haue ben, that of this fyrſt tempa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature and moiſtnes with the heat man ſhalbe engendred, who ſhuld reſt in the place of his byrthe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in any other, whiche he knoweth not. Now we wyl begin by this region, and after we haue ſpoken a lyttle of <hi>Aphtique,</hi> one of the thre partes of the worlde (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the ſame alſo is oure boke deuyded in thre.) We wyl re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſe in the fyrſt place of the cytua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the countrey of <hi>Ethiope,</hi> and maners of the nations which inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byte there, and after by order, we wyll ſet forth the diſcription of all other regions and nations, as wel as we can poſſible. And for that I wolde not ſeme altogether ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. I wyll ſome what more to en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryche my booke, entreate of more
<pb facs="tcp:13062:28"/>
then the Frenche auctoure wryteth of as well in this parte folowynge the deuiſion of the worlde in foure: as alſo to enlarge the diſcription of <hi>Ethiope,</hi> with a bryefe and general diſcription of <hi>Aphrique,</hi> and many other anotacions, accordynge to the iudgement of <hi>Pomponius Mela.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>A diuiſion of the vvorlde into foure partes. Ca. iii.</head>
            <p>AS touchynge the ſame mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that thynge which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all, what ſoeuer thynge it is, whervnto we haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the worlde and of heauen. It is one thynge and comprehendethe in one compaſe him ſelfe &amp; al thinges. In hys parte is dyfference. From whence the ſonne dothe ſprynge, it is named the Orient or Eaſt. And
<pb facs="tcp:13062:28"/>
there as it falleth it is named the Occidente or the weſt. That waye where his courſe doth lye, it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the South And on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarye parte the North. And in the middes of the ſame is the earthe on hyghe, and is gyrded rounde about wyth the ſee. And the ſame deuyded from the eaſt to the weſt into two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the which ar called <hi>Hemiſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe</hi> hath fyne diſtyncte porcyons or Zoones. Heate dothe vex the medle moſt and colde the extremes. The reſydwe maye be inhabited. They haue lyke tymes of the yere, but yet not at one time our <hi>Antich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thones</hi> doth dwell in the one, and we in the other. The ſcituation of that being vnknowne for the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heate of the plage, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene: we muſte entreate vppon this. And ſo this is extended from
<pb facs="tcp:13062:29"/>
the eaſt vnto the weſt. And for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lyeth euen ſo it is ſomthing longer than where it is brodeſt. It is all compaſſed aboute with the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccear,</hi> and receaueth of hym foure ſeas, one from the Northe and two frome the Southe, and the fourth from the weſt. They ſhalbe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their places. This firſt bring very ſtrayte and paſſynge not ten miles in bredth openeth the earth, and entrethe. And then is poured out longe and wyde and dryueth a fore him myghtely the ſee bankes, gyuing him place. And then againe they commynge together verye nygh, it is dryuen into ſuch a ſtrayt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is leſſe then a myle ouer. And then ſpreadeth it ſelfe agayne, but thae is very moderatly and then it goeth forthe into a more narowe place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was afore, where, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:29"/>
it is once receyued it is agayne ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye huge and great, and is ioyned vnto the poole, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is by a ſmale monthe. And all this ſame bothe where as it commethe and where as it ſpreadeth is called wyth one name our ſee. The ſtrayte entre of it commynge in, the <hi>Latynes,</hi> dothe call <hi>Fretum.</hi> where as it ſpreadeth a brode, it receyueth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers names in diuers places, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as it firſt ſtratneth it ſelfe together it is called <hi>Helles Pontus.</hi> And then <hi>Propontus</hi> where as it ſpreadeth out, where it rynneth together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne <hi>Eoſpherus</hi> of <hi>Thrace.</hi> And where agayne it powrethe out it ſelfe a brode it is called <hi>Pontus Euxinus.</hi> And there as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the poole it is called <hi>Cymi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ꝰ Boſpherus.</hi> The poole it ſelfe is
<pb facs="tcp:13062:30"/>
called <hi>Meot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> By this ſee and two noble ryuees called <hi>Tanais</hi> and <hi>Nil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the hole worlde is deuyded into thre partes. The ryuer <hi>Tanais</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynge from the Northe towarde the Southe rynnethe all moſte in to the myddeſt of the poole <hi>Meotis.</hi> and from the contrary part <hi>Nilus</hi> rynneth into the ſee. And all that lande that is from the ſtrayte vnto thoſe fluddes on the one ſide we cal <hi>Africa.</hi> And on the other ſide <hi>Euro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe,</hi> vnto <hi>Nilus, Africa,</hi> vnto <hi>Tanais Europe.</hi> And al that euer is beyond is called <hi>Aſia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The diſcripcion of the Conntreye of Ethiope, and the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente maners of the Ethiopiens. p Ca. iiii</head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:30"/>
               <hi>EThiope</hi> is a region deuyded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two partes. Thone parte is called <hi>Aſie.</hi> thother is <hi>Aphricke.</hi> The ſame which at this day is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Indes towarde the ſonne ryſynge, is enuironned with the rede ſee, and with the ſee of <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> towardes the North it is bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge on the countrey of <hi>Libie</hi> and <hi>Egepte</hi> towardes Occidente, and doth ioyne to the fortheſt <hi>Lible</hi> of the parte reſtynge, the whiche is ſet on the ſyde of <hi>Midy</hi> and ioyned to the other <hi>Ethiope,</hi> and was ſo called by a name <hi>Athiopes</hi> ſonne of <hi>Vulcaiue,</hi> whiche firſt raygned (as ſayth <hi>Plinie</hi>) of a Greke digeſtion <hi>Atho</hi> whiche ſignifieth burne and <hi>Oph</hi> which ſignifieth take hede, &amp; that becauſe of the approchynge nyghe to the ſoone. The countreye is continually hote, the ſame being
<pb facs="tcp:13062:31"/>
vnder the region of the <hi>Midy.</hi> This countrey draweth towardes the weſt, and the deſert towardes the Eaſt. Many ſortes of people dwell there of dyuers figures, &amp; kyndes. Some do thynke that they were the fyrſt created of almortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the true Inhabitoures of the earthe. They knowe not what bondage meaneth. They haue alwayes ben at lybertie. It is ſayde that religion and the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moneyes for theyr Goddes were fyrſt by them inuented. They haue doble vſaunce of letters. The let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which be called holye, are for the priſtes of lawes vſage &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely knowne, the other be for the common people. The fygures of their letters were not ſuch that of them myghte be lykened two ſela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, but moore lyker to the oute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb facs="tcp:13062:31"/>
parts of men and creatures, and to be compared to ſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that artificers occupy. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one of the fygures had thre proper ſignifications. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. The figure of <hi>Milan,</hi> by the whiche was ſygnyfyed celeritie or quiknes. By the fygure of one <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile,</hi> was ſignified euyll. By the fygure of <hi>Locil</hi> was ſignified take hede and preſeruation, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of all other figures euerye one to his proprietie ſignified ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye thynges They which preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſigne of Incence amongeſte the priſtes were holden moſt holy, and therefore they were axcepted with the kynge and worſhypped of all the people as men endued wyth deuinitie, which was reputed to be ſente by the deuyne prouydence. The kynge was bounde to lyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:32"/>
to the ordinaunce of their lawes, and in al his affayres to be ruled as the faſhion of the contrey, he coulde puniſhe no malefactours nor rewarded good doers, but wolde ſende one of his offycers to hym whiche is ordeyned to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhed, geuynge him charge to ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifye to him death. As ſoone as he ſhulde ceaſe ſpekynge to the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, incontinently after, he ſhal go into his houſe and kyl him, with out remedy or other queſtion to be axed. There is much honour attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btted by them to the kynge, for as often as they ſhall perceyue him to be ſycke in any part of his body, or what cauſe ſo euer it may be, they of the court, wyll in good grey take the lyke deceaſe in the ſawe parte where the kinge is ſicke of, for they iudge if to be health full for theim,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:32"/>
that if ſo be it, the kynge ſhuld loſe either his legge or arme, that they myght alſo be pertycypent, of the lyke calamytie. Alſo they ſay that they which be ſeruantes with the kynge after they knowe that he is deade, do ſeke alſo theyr owne dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and that is in wytneſſe or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial of the true amyte betwene theyr kynge and them. The ſame death ſayth they doth tourne them to greeate honour.</p>
            <p>The moſt part of the people of that countrey do commonly go naked, becauſe it is ſo hote, onely they do couer theyr members with ſhepes ſkynnes, and other ſome of theym haue couerynges hangynge frome theyr heare (with the whiche they be interlaced) vnto the myddle of theyr bodyes. They haue no frute nor grayne, but of lyttle Palmes,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:33"/>
and yet there is but a ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, ſome of the people lyue with hearbes and lyttle rootes of trees together with fleſhe and mylke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meroe</hi> was the capitall towne, in that realme, and is an Ilonde in forme of a tryangle within the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Nylo,</hi> and dothe extende al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thre thouſand <hi>Stades</hi> It was inhabited at the beginning by ſhep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herdes giuen holly to the chaſe and by laboures, who had in theyr poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſions the myndes of golde. <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dote</hi> doth reſyte that the <hi>Macro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biens</hi> (whiche be people in <hi>Ethiope</hi>) do moore eſteme tynne and lether, then golde, in ſo muche that the Imbaſſadours which kynge <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſes</hi> ſent into that countrey, came home cheyned together lyke priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in great cheynes of gold, they haue in that countrey great plenty
<pb facs="tcp:13062:33"/>
of golde and Evene wodde. They kyl the Olyphantes and eate them They haue Lyons, Leopardes, Vnycornes, Dragons, the which by the nomber of knottes, they make of theyr tayles do kyl the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphantes. There is found in that countrey certeyne kynde of ſtones, as the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acinthe,</hi> and the <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſt.</hi> they do gather Peper there Theyr bowes belonge and burnt at the ende. The women of that countrey vſe to go a warfare them ſelues, all lyke to the men. And they haue for the moſt part theyr lyppe perſed, or thruſte thorowe with a knyfe, and thorowe the ſame paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a ring of copper. Some of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do worſhyp the ſon ryſynge, other ſome the ſonne going downe, ſome vſe to caſt the dead bodies into the ryuers, other ſome do encloſe them
<pb facs="tcp:13062:34"/>
in veſſels of earth and kepe them a hole yere in theyr houſes and ſo do worſhyp the deade bodyes, &amp; with great ſeremonie maketh offerynge of the fyrſt fruite gathered. Some wrytethe that they vſe of cuſtome to choſe him kyng which doth paſſe all other in the ſcience of bryngyng vp beaſtes, and ſtronge of bodye. Theyr kyng had this prerogatyue of an olde and auncient cuſtome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the prieſtes of the cytie of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phis,</hi> that he myght by his officer commaund which of them he wold to kyll them ſelues, and to apoynte in theyr ſteade and place whom he pleaſe. They do beleue that there is an euerlaſtyng God, and he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che made all thynges and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the whole world. Ageyne they do beleue there ſhulde be an other mortal, the which god (as they ſay
<pb facs="tcp:13062:34"/>
they knowe not. They haue theyr kynge in ſuche reuerence that they lyken hym to theyr God, for they ſay he hath merited more praiſe for a publyke cauſe, and worthyer of honour then theyr God. This lyke hath ben from the beginnynge alſo the eſtate of <hi>Ethiope.</hi> Suche hath ben theyr ceremonies and maner; of lyuynge. Neuer the leſſe Marc <hi>Anthony Sabellique</hi> (out of whom we haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt part which we haue and wyll rehearſe) dothe ſay that he dyd vnderſtande of the true and ryght men of the countrey that the kynge of Ethiope whiche we call pretian or preſt Iohn who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal <hi>Gian,</hi> that is to ſay ſtronge is of ſo great a perſonage and blud, that vnder him he hath threſcoore and two other kynges, and that is the chyefe of the Churche in his
<pb facs="tcp:13062:35"/>
kyngdome be all gouerned by him. There be vnder hym in his kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome a greate nomber of Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhops, and eche of theim Ageyne haue at the leaſt vnder theyr iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction twenty byſhops. They ſay more, that princes and noble bluds do eary the croſſe before them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they go abrode. In lyke caſe, they cary a veſſell made of golde fylled with earthe, and by that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be warned of the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall condicion by one of the ſayd ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections, and by the other of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Ieſus Chriſt. The pryeſtes do mary wyues, to the ende they maye encreaſe, alwayes prouyded when theyr fyrſt wyues be deade it is forbydden theym to take an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theyr Temples be of greate hyghneſſe and large, and farre ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher then ours, They haue dyuers
<pb facs="tcp:13062:35"/>
couentes and orders of religion. As of ſaynct Anthony ſaynct <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enick,</hi> ſaynt <hi>Auguſtin</hi> and other Their aparel is not of one certeine coloure, but as the ſupprior wold permit them to weare. They haue a great deuoſion to our bleſſed and holy virgin Marye, and to ſaynct Thomas, which is called <hi>Didimus,</hi> They do ſurely thynke that theyr kyng which is called <hi>Gram</hi> is come of the ſeade of <hi>Dauid:</hi> Of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they eſteme their generation to haue of longe tyme continued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll theſe preſentes. The kynge is not blacke as other of the people of <hi>Ethiope</hi> be he is bothe of face and body whyte. The olde kyng of the countrey is called <hi>Garama,</hi> he is not encloſed in a wall. They dyd buylde a great nombre of tentes, and pauylions diſpoſed by order,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:36"/>
garnyſhed with tapeſtry, &amp; wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght with ſylke. The kynge of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome doth neuer kepe hym ſelfe together in houſes, and cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters waled two houres, and why? They iudge it to be a thinge of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy &amp; diſhoneſtie. They obſerue this kynde of doynge for a lawe, at al tymes in warres they can fynde a mylion of men, fyne hundreth O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphantes, and with them a greate nomber of horſes and Camelles, &amp; ageyne by occaſion of a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles which chaunced, there is al a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout the countreys many bandes of his ſouldiours, and they which do diſcend be marked with a croſſe the which is prynted with an hote fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in what place ſo euer they come it ſhall appere vpon theim. They vſe in theyr warres Iauelynges. The hygheſt degree of dingnitie is
<pb facs="tcp:13062:36"/>
preſthod. The ſeconde degree is to be gyuen to the ſage men, whiche they cal <hi>Balſamos</hi> and <hi>Panquez,</hi> they eſteme gretly innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, and for kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege they put theſe two vertues in the fyrſt place of wyſedome. The thyrde degree of reputacion is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the ſtate of the nobles, atter the whiche foloweth thoſe whiche be in the eſtate of a Prince. The Iudges ſayth theyr myndes, when there is any queſtion of the death of a man, and doth ſend their myndes in wrytynge to the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the towne, which they call <hi>Lycomegia,</hi> which doth preſent the kynges perſon. They haue lawes regiſtred in wrytynge, and do iuge al thinges as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe thought good to be done with Iuſtyce and equitie. The man founde in anultry and condemned for the ſame, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:13062:37"/>
pay for amendes the fourth parte of theyr goodes. when that the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man is lykewyſe founde the correc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the houſe, where ſhe offended, and as they of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal thynke theim ſelues diſhonored, ſo to puniſhe her. The men and women do weare whyte apparel ſet with pearles, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth theyr clothes euen to their fete and theyr ſleues be neither open be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore nor behynde. They vſe al co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in theyr aparel except blacke, and that they weare not becauſe it is a dolefull token, the whiche they are accuſtomed to weare .xl. dayes after any of theyr frendes dye. At noble mennes tables, they are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for theyr fyrſt meſe with hard fleſhe, which they cut vp properly, and do pouder it with ſpices, and with good appetyde eate the ſame.
<pb facs="tcp:13062:37"/>
They do neuer apparel themſelues in wollen cloth, theyr apparel is of lynnen &amp; ſylke. They haue dyuerſe languages amongeſt them and do apply them ſelues to tyl the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. All the nacions of <hi>Libie</hi> whiche be on this ſyde of <hi>Ethiopie</hi> to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnto the <hi>Occident</hi> do folow the errour of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and do lyue in a maner lyke to <hi>Barbaries,</hi> whiche be nowe in Egypte, and be called <hi>Maures,</hi> becauſe of the frequenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of <hi>Maures,</hi> whiche greued not this countrey of <hi>Libie</hi> ſo much as the <hi>Sarazines</hi> in the euyl tyme that ſo greate alteracion and mutacion chaunced in this worlde and that the aunciente lawes and creances, was as well thorowe al the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and nacions chaunged as alſo theyr names There is a lake wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in the bodyes whiche be waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:13062:38"/>
withall dothe ſhyne lyke as they were annoynted with oyle. The ſame is feble alſo and weake that the thynges which do fal or be caſt into it, as the leaues which be nigh the ſayde lake fallyng therein doth not ſwymme vpon the water, but is receaued inwardly, and ſo ſynke downe. There be alſo meruelous byrdes with hornes, and <hi>Tragopo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mones</hi> and <hi>Pagaſi</hi> which haue eares lyke Aſſes. But into the partes to wardes the borders Southward, there is nothynge notable. Al that way is waſt, for it is interupt with waue hy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, and rather lyke freſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water bankes then ſea bankes.</p>
            <p>And from thens there is a greate cooſte and withoute inhabytance. And for a certeyne tyme it was douted whether the ſea was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde or whether the earthe was
<pb facs="tcp:13062:38"/>
compaſſed about or whether <hi>Aphri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>que,</hi> beynge voyde of all fruite, dyd extende it ſelfe without ende. But yf it be ſo that <hi>Hamo</hi> of <hi>Carthago</hi> whan he was ſent by his countrey folkes to ſerche out the countreies, ofter he had paſſed the mouthes of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and went a compaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute a great part of <hi>Aphrique,</hi> he made report, that he dyd not lacke ſea. But that he wanted victuall. A certeyne man called <hi>Eudoxus</hi> in the tyme of oure graundefathers, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he fled away from <hi>Lathy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> Kynge of Alexandria wente forth by the <hi>Arabians</hi> baie (as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi> affirmeth) and was caryed thorowe by thoſe ſeas euen vnto <hi>Gades</hi> where there is certeine thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of that border knowen. For beyonde thoſe places which as we haue ſayd before be deſerte. There
<pb facs="tcp:13062:39"/>
be dume people which vſeth ſignes for ſpech, other hath tonges with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. ſome lacke there tonges other ſome alſo haue theyr lyppes c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>auynge together, ſauynge that they haue an hole vnder their noſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trelles, where they couet to drinke, but whan they haue lyſte to eate, they take the corne ſprynging here and there, &amp; be reported to receaue one corne at once. Theſe be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. yet not ſo admirable as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Truelye they be worthy of parpetuall memory and prayſe as well for their lyuynge as alſo for the obedyence to theyr prynce. For howe much is it to be accounted to vs for diſhonor beyng Chriſtians, reaſonable creatures, endued with celeſtiall knowledge, and inſtructed in godly lawes to ſhowe more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to our magiſtrates the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:39"/>
the Infydels to theyr gouernours. what rebuke do they meret and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, whiche knowe the worde of God, and yet neyther obeye the Quene nor her godly procedinges? Where as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Ethenekes</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge the true God ne his lawes, do notwithſtandyng lyue a purer lyfe then they. Well I wyſhe all men wolde haue ſhame layde before theyr eyes as a glaſſe to loke in, that they myght therby be more aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to do euyl, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Infydels.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:40"/>
            <head>The diſcription of Egypt, and the maners of the Egyptiens Cha. v.</head>
            <p>EGypt is a countreye in <hi>Aphric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> (whiche to the iudgement of ſome) is nighe to <hi>Aphrique,</hi> and this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey is ſo called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a brother of <hi>Danaus</hi> whiche had the name Egyptus, &amp; was before called <hi>Aeria</hi> This countrey as Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſayth in his fyfte boke, is of the ſyde of the Orient by the rede ſee, and the region <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> towardes the Occedente of the countreye of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent,</hi> to the reſidue of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of <hi>Aphricque,</hi> The ſame dothe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende from the <hi>Midy</hi> to <hi>Ethiope</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes the ſyde of <hi>Septentrion</hi> to the ſea of Egypte, There was
<pb facs="tcp:13062:40"/>
ſometyme greate Cyties as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Abidos, Alexadria, Babilon, Memphis,</hi> and at this tyme <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aniete</hi> and <hi>Caire</hi> or <hi>Alcir,</hi> the which is the reſidens of <hi>Soldan.</hi> In Egypte (as ſaith Platon) there is no raine, and yet is the earth verye fruitfull, &amp; al by reaſon of the ryuer of <hi>Nile,</hi> whiche is deuyded in ſuche ſorte and made in fourme of a tryangle, for the which ſigne there is a word in Greke called <hi>Deltae,</hi> ſo that coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey is called <hi>Deltae</hi> by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> many and ſoundrye fluddes which come euery yere from the ryuer of <hi>Nile</hi> after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drougthe of the ſomer Some men iudged that it was an Ilande, becauſe of the circuite that the ſayde <hi>Nile</hi> had made all about the countrey. The <hi>Egyptiens,</hi> were the firſt inuentures of .xii. Goddes, and beganne to buylde Temples,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:41"/>
Aulters, Images, and ingraued in ſtones figures of diuers beſtes. The thynges whiche be iſſued out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Ethiopiens</hi> ſhal ſuffycyently declare the ſame to vs, who hathe ben the inuentures of theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (as <hi>Diodore Cilicien</hi> ſaythe) Theyr wyues of an olde &amp; auncient cuſtome do vſe to occupy marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: vyſe, to kepe Hoſtyllerye and vyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyllynge houſes &amp; do alſo trafyke, wherevpon the men do gyue theim ſelues to make lynnen clothe and to cary fardles vpon theyr heades, where the women do not carye but vpon theyr ſhoulders, as our men do here in Ingla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Moreouer they vſe to make water agaynſt a wall lyke vnto our men, &amp; the men cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge downe to the grounde lyke as our women do here, all neſſeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes in the houſe the women do, and
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:41"/>
after that is done they go a brode a bankettynge. Their cuſtone is to aſſemble together with theyr Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. The menne chyldren be not compelled to kepe theyr parentes, but the doughters, many of theim in tyme paſte (when any of theyr frendes dyed) were accuſtomed to pole their heare &amp; let their beardes growe longe. The <hi>Egyptiens</hi> to the contrarye ſhaue their beardes, &amp; let the heare of theyr hedde growe. They kned the dowe there whych they make breade with their fete, and worketh the earth with theyr handes. This hathe ben a perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler faſſion to all thoſe whych were diſſended from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as the Grekes writeth) to cyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſſe their me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers and preuites. The men be clothed with double apparell. The women do weare but one wydde at a time.
<pb facs="tcp:13062:42"/>
They haue two kyndes of vſages of letters. The one is for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Priſtes The other is for the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Notwithſtandynge they haue both the ſame of the <hi>Ethiopiens.</hi> The Priſtes for the ſpace of thre dayes be accuſtomed to haue the vermyn &amp; other fylthenes of theyr bodyes taken awaye becauſe they feare to do ſeruyce with the fylthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes about them. They are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mablye apparelled in linnen They ſowe no Beanes. It is defended by their lawes, and whye? becauſe they eſteme them vncleane. They waſhe thre tymes in the daye wyth cold water, &amp; .ii, times in the night They wyll not eate the heades of theyr Beſtes vntyll ſuche tyme as they be ſacreficed. Iudgynge them to be curſed by execrations durynge the tyme of theyr ſacrefyces. They
<pb facs="tcp:13062:42"/>
do ſell the ſayd heades to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt ſtraungers, and yf they can fynd no man that wyl by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They be caſt into the ryuer of <hi>Nile.</hi> All the ſacrifices of Egipt. Be of Oxen whiche neuer before ſerued. The Calues and Kyne be not ſaccrefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for that the ſame Beaſtes are dewe to be offred to <hi>Iſis</hi> theyr God. They lyue by a kynd of meat made of Wheate and Rye, and of drynke made of branne, for in that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey there is no wynes. They eate alſo of a certeyne fyſſhe parte hardened and dried in the ſonne, and parte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in ſellers, whiche is moyſte. Some tyme they eat byrdes which be ſalted and made harde as a cruſt of breade. Morouer the noble men in their bankeres do preſent wylde Duckes, both mayles &amp; femayles. Whan they fynde a companye ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13062:43"/>
at a ſupper, one amongſt them taketh out of hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uget an Image of death made of wodde or payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted cloth of halfe a yard longe, they ſhoweth it to euery man at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſayth. Eate and make good chere, after that thou arte deade thou ſhalbe lyke to thys pycture. If the yonger do recontre or mete the elder, he gyueth place to hym, &amp; tourneth to hym wyth reuerence, and in thus doynge they reſemble the <hi>Lacedemoniens.</hi> Whan the yonger doth ouer take the elder by the way ſhoweth worſhip and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d on the kne. They haue) as <hi>Haeſte</hi> wryteth) gownes of lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen borders downe to theyr knes, called <hi>Caſiliers,</hi> &amp; aboue the ſame they weare other whyt garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, but no wollen cloth. Al they which in olde tyme excelle in knowledge,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:43"/>
or had eſtablyſſhed lawes for the common weale. as cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellers went fyrſt to the Egyptiens to learne theyr knowledge and doctrine, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche knowledge they paſſed all other as theſe report. <hi>Orpheus</hi> the Poet, <hi>Homere, muſeus Melampodes Dedalus, Licurgus Lacedemonien</hi> and alſo <hi>Solon</hi> of <hi>Athenes Platon.</hi> Philoſopher, <hi>Phithagoras</hi> the <hi>Sami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> &amp; his ſcoller <hi>Samolxis, Eudoxus Mathematicien, Democritus, Inopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> borne in the Ilande of <hi>Chios Moyſes</hi> the hebrew, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo that the Priſtes of Egypt glorifyed that they founde them in theyr bokes, Wherfore me thinke it is very neceſſary to ſpeake more of their fachio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, maners, &amp; lyuings to thende we myght knowe that whiche they aboue named had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of them and other nations. For
<pb facs="tcp:13062:44"/>
ſo (as ſayth <hi>Ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alde.</hi>) In the boke that <hi>Apulie</hi> dyd wryte vppon the golden Aſſe, that manye of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chions and doynges was gathered out of the ſeremonies of the <hi>Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens,</hi> as to weare germentes, the men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to weare a crowne, to make alters, to go a proceſſyon, to ſynge muſycke, to do adoration, to pray and many other thynges. The Kynges of Eypte (as writeth <hi>Diodore Silicien</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond boke) dyd not as oure Prynces in theyr tyme whiche helde their wylles for lawes, and lyued in euyl order, but their conueruacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was to be noted in that they lyued accordynge to theyr ordynaunces. They haue no bonde men nor ſlaues borne, as they haue in other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries. Noble mens chyldren ſerue them in theyr houſes, as well of Priſtes, as alſo
<pb facs="tcp:13062:44"/>
of others, they muſt be twentye yeres olde and ſuch was choſen as hadde knowlege, to thend that the Prynce moued, by the preſens of his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes (who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were alwayes next to his perſon) ſhoulde not be fanteſied and mynded to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actes, but of vertue, for the Kynges do nothing of them ſelues worthy of reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they haue at all tymes to councell theym other that be wyſe alſo, there is certeyne houres appoynted as well in the nyght as in the daye, at the whyche tyme the Kynge ſhall vnderſtande the affayres commytted to him by their lawes. At his vpryſynge he ſhall receaue all complayntes exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byted vnto hym to the end he may knowe al that ſhal nede to be done. Euerye thynge is diſpatched in tyme and in his place oppoſited
<pb facs="tcp:13062:45"/>
by good conduxcion. After that is done, they waſſhe their bodyes in the preſens of many noble &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, putteth on a ſumptuous robe, and makes ſacrifyce to theyr Goddes. The cuſtome of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Prelate amongſt al the priſtes is to leade nyghe to the aulter the beaſtes, and to prayſe theyr Gods with a loude voyce the Kynge next to hym, and the people aſſyſtynge. They alſo pray for the health and proſperitie of theyr Kynge, whiche hath done true iuſtice to his ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and afterwarde reſitynge the vertue and excellency of their ſayd Prince, as his deuoſion towardes the Goddes, humilitie to man, the kepynge of his promeſſe, Iuſtyce, magninemitie, veretie, lyberalitie, modiſtie and mercye to theim in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarines. And afterwarde do curſe
<pb facs="tcp:13062:45"/>
all malifactoures, and therby dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargethe their Kynge of blame. Imputynge his offences to hys of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycers. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that theſe ſolempnites be fynyſſhed, the Prelate doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orte the Kinge to depart according to the wyll of theyr Goddes, &amp; not to folowe the peoples aduyce of ſmale practyſe, but to haue reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte to vertue and honour. After that the ſacrifyce made of a Bull is done, the Prelate dothe rehearſe out of holye bookes ſome actes of vertue made by their prediceſſors, to admonyſhe theyr Kynge to rule after the example of theym, that is truly and iuſtlye. The aunciente lawes were not only made to mein<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne Iuſtyce, but alſo for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement of euerye thynge in all poyntes, as to eate, drynke, ſlepe, to banyſhe and to accompanye wyth
<pb facs="tcp:13062:46"/>
women. Their meates were denty: mooſte commonlye they vſe to eate Veale. They haue a certeyne mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure when they drynke wyne, that they can not paſſe the ſtynte, The which is to avoyde Ebrietie drou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes and glotenye. Inſomuche their laws were ſo wel inſtituted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it appered they were not made &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deyned by a lawier, but by a moſte perfecte Phiſicion. And it was a maruelous thynge to ſe the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens ſo perticularly and duely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theyr lawes, and not theyr wylles, but this is moore worthye of maruell to ſay that they were not inclyned to gather and accumelate goodes, by a vniuſt maner or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye vnreyſonable couetouſnes. They do punyſh no man in indyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo that their felicitie was obtempered to the lawes &amp; eſteme
<pb facs="tcp:13062:46"/>
theym whiche prayſe and glorifie them ſelfes to be ſubiectes to many paſſions in folowynge theyr owne pleaſures: in ſomuche that we may ſe they knowe theyr owne fautes, that neyther loue, heae, nor coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes coulde compel theym to do thynges whiche they knewe to be vnlawefull or preuidiciall to thoſe whiche gouerne them by prudence and councel, beſydes they haue reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect leaſt they ſhuld dyſpleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The iuſtice of the kinge to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on the other ſide is ſuche, that he hath the loue of all theym. that not onely the priſtes, but alſo the hoole people of Egypt haue a great ſolicitude or more carefulnes, and tendernes ouer the health of theyr kyng, then they haue eyther of wife chyldren or other perticuler Lorde. And when ſuch a iuſt king doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.
<pb facs="tcp:13062:47"/>
All in generall doth deploore and lament, rente theyr clothes in peeces, ſhut the churches, and are diſcoraged to commence any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke actes. By the ſpace of .lxxii. dayes. two hundreth of theim go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about the ſtreates in a ſtrange apparel as well men as women .ii. tymes a day, and ſingeth after the maner and fourme of hymmes, the vertues of theyr kynge depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And they wyll not eate the fleſh of any beſt baked, thei abſteyn them ſelues from all delicate mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as wel in drynking as alſo in ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng. They vſe no bathes, nor oint<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, nor ſleapes in beddes, nor haue not the companye of theyr wyues. So ſorowfully be they al as thoughe theyr deare chyldren were departed. And more ouer tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge this, they be wont to make
<pb facs="tcp:13062:47"/>
redy that which ſhuld ſerue for the ſepulcher, and at the laſt day, they ſhut the body within a lyttle Cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, before it is put in the ſepulcher In the ſame place there ſhalbe red accordynge to the olde cuſtome the Regeſter of all that which the king had done in his lyfe tyme, and it was permytted for euery one to ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſe him. At theſe funerals there are a great nombre of people ſome come with loud voyce to praiſe his deſeruynges and merites, other do blame his faultes, and make a gret noyſe and brute. And by this brute it hath many times hapened that diuers kynges, haue ben pluc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked away from the honour of the ſepulcher, and hauynge this feare doth ſtyre and prouoke the kynges of Egypte to lyue well and iuſtely, fearing leaſt after theyr death they
<pb facs="tcp:13062:48"/>
ſhoulde incurre into the diſpleaſure of any of theyr ſubiectes. And this is the ſtate of the kyng of this coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey. Al Egypt is deuyded into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers gouernementes, euery one of them by a name, conſtituted a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour who hath the charge of all thyngs. The reuenews of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges lands was deuided in thre par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. The firſt part to the preſtes of theyr lawe, to whome they gyue great honour, as wel for the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracion of theyr ſacramentes, as alſo for theyr knoweledge, by the which other be tought, parte of the reuenewes be employed vpon ſuch neceſſaries as ſerueth for the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and theyr owne lyuynges. they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſuffre that the miniſters of theyr gods ſhalbe poore, or that they ſhulde lacke any thynge to do ſacrifyce withall. Theſe prieſtes
<pb facs="tcp:13062:48"/>
comynge to the kynge profeſſeth to him the thynges which be to come aſwell by the ſcience of Aſtrology, as alſo by the ſorte of theyr ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. Moreouer they do rehearſe to theyr kyng bokes which be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led holly. The actes and deades of other kings, his predeceſſors bi the ſame he know the better what is expedient for him. They be not in a ſmall nombre as ye wolde ſaye two in a companye, they be franke and haue the ſecond place of aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie next to the kynge. The ſecond part of the reuenewes is to the king who doth beſtowe it for his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries as wel vpon marterial wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons for warres, as alſo the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries for his houſe, and ſhewe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie towardes the good and vertuous people. And by this his lyberalitie the comon people be not
<pb facs="tcp:13062:49"/>
burdened to pay taxes and fynes, as they do in other countreys. The thyrde parte of the reuenewes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeeh to the men of warre, to the ende they may haue the greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to put them ſelues forth in al partes dangerous, for the defence of theyr countrey. Theyr policie conſiſteth in thre maner of people, that is to ſay, labourers, herdemen and practiſers of ſcience. The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers do bye eyther of the preſts Kynge, or of men of warre, certeine grounde in the fyelde, and do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in labourynge all theyr lyfe longe vpon the ſame. And therof it commeth that they can better ſkyll to laboure and tyll the earthe, then other nacions. This induſtry and labour of theyrs is gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature from the father to the chylde, lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe the ſhepherde from the father
<pb facs="tcp:13062:49"/>
to the chylde, do kepe and noryſhe beaſtes and haue no other vocation This art and ſcience hath ben gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly augmented by the artyficers of Egypt, for that they meddle with no publyke matter, nor do exerciſe no other occupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but that which they are called to, and apoynted by theyr lawes, or learned of theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. They do iudge nothing raſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. In ſo muche they ſay that theſe thynges which be conducted poſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuely and by maturitie be of gret commodytie, and for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of ſociete and humayne lyfe,</p>
            <p>They can fynde no better meanes to expulſe or banyſhe all noughty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, then to puniſhe mulefactours and euyl doers, ſo ſhal al offenders be whypped. And they haue ſuche a reſpect that due Iuſtyce be done, that neyther for loue frendſhip, nor
<pb facs="tcp:13062:50"/>
money, the treſpaſſes of the offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dour ſhall be forgeuen, for they ſayd, theſe remiſſions to be deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of man. Wherfore in the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Cyties as in <hi>Heliopole</hi> in <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phis,</hi> and <hi>Thebes</hi> there was elected and choſen good men, to whom the correction of all cauſes was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted who do lyttle dyffer from thoſe of <hi>Areopagites</hi> of <hi>Athenes</hi> or to the ſenate of the <hi>Lacedemoniens</hi> wher there was of longe time two iudges conſtituted. They do apere alwayes to the nomber of xxx. and they choſe ſome of the moſte lykeſt amonge them to be preſident. And ageyne there is gyuen to theym an other ſuperior by the Cytizens. The kynge doth fynde all the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaries as lyuynges, but the ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by the king to be more honorablye ſerued then
<pb facs="tcp:13062:50"/>
the inferiours. He that is principal of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath a cheine of golde hange at his necke, wherunto is tyed an Image wel garnyſhed with preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones. This cheyne is called verytie. In ſo much that preſident ſhulde ſignifie to all menne that he which was apoynted to heare their cauſes, by the cheyne ſhulde preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t veritie, and with truth to way all thynges. Ageyne theyr lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynynge in .viii. bookes, brought amongeſt them. This was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, that the accuſer ſhuld bring in written the cauſes of the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; to certifie the iudge in forme and maner as it was done (Is the hurte doone to an other was a queſtion.) To the defendant there was gyuen tyme to aunſwere the plaintifes obiection, and to pourge him ſelfe or auoyde the fault, or els
<pb facs="tcp:13062:51"/>
to deny al and be cleare. Moreouer they gyue audyence to the accuſer. Fynally after that they haue benne harde two tymes before the iuges They take deliberacion, that done the iudge tourneth the Image to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the true and feythfull par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, and doth pronounce iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Seyng nowe by chaunce we haue fallen into this paſſage, and taken vpon vs this iourney in the formal declaracions, it wolde be moſt beſt to rehearſe ſome olde and auncient lawes of the Egyptians, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that we may know the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other, as thoſe that be euyll to ſhone, and the other that be good &amp; profytable to folow. Al Periurers were corporally punyſhed, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as men diſprayſynge the religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the goddes, in ſo doynge they had vyolated the fayth to man, the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:51"/>
which is no other thyng then a true lyne of humayne ſocietie and felow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp, he that in the hygh way ſhal mete any man which hath ben pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by theues or robbers, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge able, wolde not runne to take them, was holden coulpable of the inconueniens and miſfortune hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnto the man. And if ſo be it, he coulde not folowe him. Yet was he bonde to come before the Iuſtice and there to declare the cauſe, and to preſent him ſelfe as an accuſer a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt the thyefe. The peyne that was appoynted to him that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the law was: that he ſhuld endure a nombre of ſtrypes with a rod, and not to eate nor drynke for the ſpace of thre hoole dayes. The falſe accuſer is puniſhed as a great tranſgreſſer. Al the Egypcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wer
<pb facs="tcp:13062:52"/>
bounde to brynge theyr names in wrytynge, and the ſtate of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of theyr countrey he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in that place was founde a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or gat his lyuyng by an vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way, as vſerye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſuche lyke, was put to death. The man whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che kylleth an other, whether he be free or bounde, was iudged to dye. for murtherers or thoſe which com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit homicede, they be not curious to haue the lawes paſſe vpon them The perſon dead, preſent deathe to the manſlers, ſo by that the nobles of the contrey be in ſurety and out of feare. The father which kyll the chylde is not put to deathe, but for the ſpace of thre dayes &amp; thre nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, he is continually nyghe death, beynge accompanied with a certein nombre of ſeriantes. And their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:13062:52"/>
is, that thoughe they commyt this cryme, yet ought not to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed for they iudge that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taketh awaye ageyne but the lyfe whiche before he gaue to his chylde, and it is ſufficient for him to be afflicted by continual repentance and dollour he taketh for his euyll deade, and by this meanes it ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to theym that other fathers were admoniſhed not to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the lyke. They haue a ſharpe puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the paradices and manſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Fyrſte they are with a ſharpe poynted toole thruſt thorowe, and afterwarde ſet vpon a great heape of thornes, and there be bruſed, for they eſteeme manſlauter to be the greateſt cryme that a man can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt to put hym to deathe whiche wolde lyue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:53"/>If a women with chylde had done an offence and condempned to dye, execution ſhulde not haue ben done vntyll ſhe hadde ben delyuered of chylde, for feare that the infaunte in her wombe not treſpaſſynge ſhulde be puniſſhed with the treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſer. And for one faute two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to be punyſſhed. He that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battayle obeyethe not hys Capy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne is not put to deth, but incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in a notable infamie to the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of his honour. They haue ſuche a regarde to their honoures, that they eſteme the dyſtruction of theyr name worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth it ſelfe. The tongues of them be cutte out which do reueyle to theyr enemyes the ſecretes of publyke matters. All clyppers of money, Forgers of falſe Coyne, Changers of weyght and marke, Grauers of anye
<pb facs="tcp:13062:53"/>
face ſcripture or writyng, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter featters of letters haue theyr two Thombes cutte of, to thende thoſe partes of the bodye whiche had done the offence ſhoulde beare the payne and punyſhment, &amp; were ſuffred notwithſtandynge to lyue for others examples. They haue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo a greuous puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. for the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche occupyeth parforce the free women, that is. ſhall haue his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers cut of. By that one euyll acte (ſay they) he commyteth thre cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Fyrſt he hath defiled the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Secondly he hath commyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted force and vyolence. Thyrdly he let increaſe of chylder, or at the leſt ſtaynned the parentage and blode. He whiche is taken in adulterye ſhall ſuffre great tourmentes, and in the ſyght of the woman his noſe ſhalbe cut of. by that meanes they
<pb facs="tcp:13062:54"/>
wyll depreue him of part of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, the whiche loſt, in contynent loſeth his beutye. We fynd in auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that <hi>Bocchoris</hi> was the inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the lawes obſerued among the Egyptiens concernyng world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters. This amongſt alother was ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money lent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a byll or recogniſence, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower without fraude to repaye agayne to the Appreſter for they holde this oppinion. That the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe and fayth is of great efficacy and vertue. They dyd defende that any vnreaſonable vſerars ſhould be had in theyr countrey. Alſo they woulde that no man ſhoulde haue theyr bodies bounde for any dette. Thynkyng it is ſuffyciente to haue theyr goodes bounde and not their bodyes to be ſubiecte to no other thynges but to the prefermente of all publyke
<pb facs="tcp:13062:54"/>
like matters. They the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues dyd fynd this to be repungna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt reaſon that the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of warre which put theym ſelues forth in infinitte dangers for the cauſe of the come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale, to be caryed to pryſon (as they were oftymes) by reaſon of ſuche dettes as they toke vp at v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye. The lyke to this lawe there was traunſported by <hi>Solon</hi> to the <hi>Athenes,</hi> and was called <hi>Siſatee,</hi> By the which they wold not ſuffre that the bodye of a Citiziner ſhuld be kept in pryſon for moneye taken vp at vſerye. Moreouer the ſayde lawes the <hi>Ethiopiens</hi> obſerue, one particular law as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theues by the whiche it was eſtablyſhed that all they whiche had ſtolne any thynge ſhulde brynge the ſtolne before the hygh Prieſt, and to giue him their names in writynge. In
<pb facs="tcp:13062:55"/>
lykewyſe he which had the robery done to, muſt come before the high Prieſt. and declare what he hathe loſt, the daye and tyme whan, and how the robbery was committed. ſo by that meanes the thynges loſt be recouered. Alwayes it was prouyded that the fourth parte of the ſtolne goodes the robber ſhulde haue. To make this lawe ther was certeyne lawyers that conſydered wyth them ſelues that it ſhulde be vnpoſſible to dryue out of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey all theues, thought it therfore moſt expedient to fynde the wayes that ſuche gentyll men as had loſt theyr goodes myght be reſtored to them agayne: made this lawe that the fourthe parte ſhoulde be to the thefe, and the reſt to the howner. The eſtate of mariage is not in the ſame vniforme amongſt the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiens
<pb facs="tcp:13062:55"/>
as it was with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the priſtes coulde take but one wyfe in mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, the other as manye as they wolde or coulde meynteyne. They thynke the chyld is neuer Illigite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metly begotten. I ſuppoſe they be ingendred of a woman ſlaueſſe. for that the man doth iudge the chyld to be God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman which bare him in her bely to ſerue for no other purpoſe but to nourſe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may lyue. The hole charge the father is at with the chylde from his Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye vntyll he come to age, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue .xx. <hi>Drachimes</hi> whiche is ten pens Englyſhe. The Prieſtes do in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtructe the chyldren with holye let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and good bookes. They alſo teache them their ſcyences as <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrie Arithimetique.</hi> They do not ſtudy to learne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feites of warres, neyther exercyſe they mornynge,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:56"/>
nor the arte of muſycke, they haue this opinion. That mournynge is pernetious for yonge Infantes, &amp; muſycke vnprofytable, as to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe vnto them great infamation. The maners to heale malydies and diſſeaſes is to obſerue a dyet, or to prouoke to vomet: for ſeynge (as they do ſaye) that all ſyckneſſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperfluitie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of meates, they can fynde no better medycyne to helpe the ſycke patient, then to folow the aboue named rurle. The men of warre do ſpende nothynge to haue Barbers or Phiſicions, for that at the ſole and onely charge of the common weale there be Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſounde which do heale theym whan they be hurt. They haue cer: tayne kynd of medycens left them in wrytyng by theyr predyceſſors, whiche be regeſtred in bookes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:13062:56"/>
holy. If a man obſeruynge the maner of the medycens conteynyng in theyr bookes, had not holpen the ſycke patient he was exempted by their lawe, and put in fault, but yf he hadde appoynted or other wyſe miniſtred other medicene, then in the ſayde bokes were ſpecified, and that the patiente was not helped but dyed. The Phiſicion was alſo condempned to dye. This law was inſtituted by the lawyers, for they iudged it a ſtraunge thyng and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable for the ſycke man to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uente a newe maner of Phiſycke, whan he had ben a longe tyme vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited with a deſeaſe, vnder the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of a newe experiens to haſſard the lyfe of the parſon. The Egygti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens aboue all other nations, were ſubiectes to Idolytrye, amongſte other thynges they dyd not onelye worſhyp
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:57"/>
the lyuynge beaſtes, but alſo the deade, as cattes, dogges, &amp; wolfes, for they where not a ſhamed to be ſuche gret Idolyters, but glorified therin, and thought therby to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to them ſelues and to theyr Goddes great honour, They wold go about the townes &amp; cyties with the Images of the ſayde beaſtes, ſhowynge (as they went) what beaſtes they were and howe they honoured theim. Whan that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd beaſtes be departed, they wrappe them in a lynnen ſhete: That done, they bowe them ſelues downe and knocke their breſtes. They kepe theyr beaſtes dentily, for they giue theym to eate whete flower myxte with mylke, this they haue gyuen to them ordinerlye, To the other beaſtes whyche eate nothynge but harde fleſhe, was gyuen byrdes &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13062:57"/>
large money ſpent vpon them. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be deade, the people ſhowe them ſelues ſo ſorowful as though it were for the death of their owne chyldren. Manye tymes they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe vpon the ſumptuous bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of the ſayde beaſtes more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr owne ſubſtance draweth to.</p>
            <p>In ſo much when kynge <hi>Ptolomee Lagus</hi> reigned it chanced that ther was an Oxe in the cytie of <hi>Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phis,</hi> which dyed for age.<note place="margin">A talent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> is .v.C.li <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arlynge Hebraitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> talentun vulgariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is .ii. hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth and poundes ſyxti my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes is a hundrel drachmes a drachm is .iii. ſhil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyngs .iii pens.</note> The burienge of the ſayde oxe coſte his keper o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and aboue the ordinarie expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which he had ſpent vpon him al his lyfe tyme the ſome of fyfty ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes of ſyluer which he borowed of the ſayde kynge <hi>Ptolome,</hi> Theſe thynges ſhuld ſeme meruelous yet not ſo meruelus as credible to ſome men to beholde the ſumptuous bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryenge of the dead beaſtes, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:13062:58"/>
the Egyptians vſe. So often as theſe thynges chaunce, al the paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and frendes of the dead goeth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout the ſtreates, theyr heare of theyr heades all blouddy lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vntyl ſuche tyme as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is vnder the ground. Theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes gyue them occaſion ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to waſhe them ſelues, to eate delicate meates, or to drynke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt drynkes, nor to weare ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous apparel, They haue three ſortes of tombes. The fyrſt be gor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gious and coſtly. The ſeconde be not ſo cooſtely. The laſte be of a lyttle value. The fyrſt doth coſt a tallant of ſyluer. The ſecond .xx. mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, the thyrde a lytle or no certein ſomme, but at ſomtyme more, and leſſe. They whiche make the fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals haue it by patremoni. That is after theyr fathers death, the ſone make the ſepulchers, and he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tethe
<pb facs="tcp:13062:58"/>
all the expenſes and charges that it myght coſt. After that the pryce is made with him. The corps is gyuen him to burye for the price agreed of before. They whiche haue the charge to open &amp; enbalme the body be called <hi>Saleurs,</hi> and be had in honour and reputacion, for that the prieſtes accompany theim to the temple. The officers be rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about the coffin and corps, and one amongeſt them doth take all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trelles out of the belly, except that which belong to the raynes of the backe, the which once plucked forth be gyuen to an other to waſſhe in wyne of <hi>Phenice</hi> together with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwete odours. This done they do annoint the body fyrſt with oint<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of Cedre, and after with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther precious oyntmentes continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the ſpace of xxx. dayes, and to
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:59"/>
do couer it ouer with myrre and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namonde and orher ſpices, to the ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the body might be kept longe and to ſmel notwithſtandyng ſwet After that they haue thus ordered the body, it is deliuered to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes. A man lokynge vpon it ſhal not wel deſerue whther it is a dead body or one a ſleape for that al the partes, as the face, ſhoulders, han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, be hoole. Before the burienge of the deade the parentes ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to the iudges, and to the fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the deade the daye of bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge, ſayenge that the bodye ſhall paſſe the ſea. The iudges to the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of .xl. beynge redy to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the corps he which is appointed to kepe the ſhyppe ſhal brynge her to the ſhore to New Rigge and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel her. Moreouer before the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy is put into the tombe, it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:13062:59"/>
euery one to accuſe the dead yf he had ben founde to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited any euyll. The iudges gyue ſentence that he ſhal be denied the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulcher. If he had ben falſely accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the accuſer ſhuld be greuouſly puniſhed, but if no man could come and accuſe hym, the parentes ende mournynge, and begin to recite the prayſe of the deade without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge mencion of his genelogie (as the Grekes dyd) the Egiptie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s take them ſelues one lyke to an other in bludde and nobilitie. Firſt they wil rehearſe howe he hathe paſſed his youth, led his life, and the good doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he learned, and degreſſeth from that, repetynge the notable actes done in his lyfe tyme, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt all other do magnifye his goodnes towardes the gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, other vertues and qualities
<pb facs="tcp:13062:60"/>
Some children burye theyr paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in tombes. They whiche haue no ſepulcher be buried in the moſte ſtrongeſt and thyckeſt wal in theyr houſes within the which they reiſe a monument. To them which occu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pied vſery in theyr lyfe tyme, was denyed the ſepulcher, and weare brought backe ageyne, frome the temple to theyr owne houſes with out ſepulcher appointed vntyl that theyr predeceſſors with theyr ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches chaunced to theym acquyted the debities of the deade, the ſame payd, he ſhal honorably be buried. Alſo they haue this cuſtome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuer in gage to the creditoure the deade body of the debitoure. The man which had his kynſman deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſepulcher, and wyll not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme him ſhall runne into great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie and ſklaunder. In ſo muche
<pb facs="tcp:13062:60"/>
that if the ſon bye not out the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, he ſhall after his death alſo be denyed of the honoure of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher. Not withoue iuſte cauſe manye people wyll meruayl what they ment to ordeyne &amp; make thoſe lawes for affayres of the lyuynge And alſo to be ſo curious to doo that which myght rebound to the honour of the dead. It is manifeſt to vs the ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale and loue they beare to the lyfe of man, whiche woulde haue brought gladlye the ſame (by ſuch examples) clere and without ſpot. Truely the Greekes who by the fables of poetes haue paſſed in verite and truth, hath writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten of the fauorynge and cheriſhing of the good and tormentyng of the euyll. To cauſe men lead a verteus and ſincere lyfe, they thought they coulde not ſufficient, nor trauayle
<pb facs="tcp:13062:61"/>
to much. In lykewyſe the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens as wel by fables as alſo by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawful attribucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of praiſe exalted the good, and tormented the euyll. And therby they brynge or rather compell men daylye to do thynges profitable for the healthe and ſaluacion of this lyfe, that in ſo much we may ſe howe eche one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to theyr deſertes, and to the qualitie of theyr crymes recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that which they merited, and deſerued, ſo that at the laſte they were ruled and became vertuous. Wherefore we can not but iudge theſe lawes to be good, which pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke men to a deſyre to atteyn wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome and vertue, and to flye coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes and that moſte abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſeries. What do we chriſtians meane to alow that for good, which the Infidels eſteme for euyll, and
<pb facs="tcp:13062:61"/>
abhorre it. What reproche is it for vs to occupy ſo many kynde of vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes to pyll and to polle the poore, the vſerer to ſell a commoditie for one hundrethe poundes that ſcante is valued at twenty pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Alas alas I can not but lament to heare dyuers yonge gentylmen crye out vpon theſe vſerers, and alſo yonge marchaunt men whiche haue mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged theyr landes and layde their marchandyſe in paune. For if they miſſe but one day of payment, or that theyr mony is not redy at the preſcripted tyme, but come a daye or .ii. after, they wyll not receyue it but ſue the rygur of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, ſtraight way extende they the ſtatute of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaple (as they call it) with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſerued, then enter they vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe, londes, goods and al, thruſt out him, his wyfe, chyldren and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myly,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:62"/>
Yea ſo cruel be theſe vſerers that albeit for thre hundreth poun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of money lente, they haue .vii. hunereth poundes with the intreſt for a yere wel payd them, eyther of the gentylmennes landes, or poore yonge marchauntes goodes yet they wyll not gyue one peny backe agein, ſo wretched be they, though they gayne the halfe, and that there ſhulde remayne a ſmall ſomme or reſt, and fynde not ſo muche in the houſe, then ſhal the debitours bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be comitted to priſon, there to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde vntyl ful ſatiſfaction be made This haue I ſene practiſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this xiiii. months, &amp; who be they which haue occupied theſe vſeryes. and ſhewed this extremitie, but ſuch as htah profeſſed mooſt of all godlynes, and yafned them ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:13062:62"/>
holly. I ſpeake this by no perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler man, but as general griefe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me. To al ſuch corrupted con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience I ſay, not onely ſay but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo exhort them to flye this art, and practiſe a godlyer, and lette theym herein folow the councel and walke the ſteppes of the Ethenikes, for I can not but nominate theim Infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, yea more wycked then they which be not aſhamed to doo that which they vtterli deteſt. And here I make an end of the diſcription of Egypt, and the nature of the Egip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tianr, and wyll proceade to treate of other people inhabytynge in Aphrique.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:63"/>
            <head>The diſcription Of Penes or Puniciens and other people of Aphrique Capitalo .vi.</head>
            <p>THere be dyuers nations amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the <hi>Penes</hi> or <hi>Puniciens.</hi> The <hi>Adrimachides</hi> do drawe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Egypte, and holde the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyons of the Egyptiens, ſauynge onely they weare theyr apparell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of the <hi>Punitiens,</hi> their wyfes do weare a cheyne of copper, and neuer do cut theyr heare. They do byte the fles betwene theyr teth when they fynde them about their bodyes, and after they do caſt them awaye. They preſent onely amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt other people of that contreye theyr doughters, and promyſethe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be faythfull to theyr kynge, and he onely to deflower them, and
<pb facs="tcp:13062:63"/>
to haue his choyſe to take of them whom he ſhal pleaſe or fantaſye. The <hi>Naſamoniens</hi> be other people verye euyll, the moſt parte of them be robbers vpon the ſea, and whan they ſe a ſhyppe a ſhore they tone vpon hir and robbeth hir, In ſomer they leaue theyr cattell all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the cooſte, and do go to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne place where there is greate plentye of fayre and good fruytes, and gathereth theym. The fruyte whiche they gather before they be rype they do leaue in the ſonne to drye. Afterwarde put mylke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and ſtampeth it, and then they do ſwalow it hole. They haue ech of them many wyfes, and haue companye with them whan theyr luſt is come vpon theym at the firſt place they tome at openly, without hauynge anye ſhame to do it in the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:64"/>
preſence of other, Lyke vnto them be the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſagetes</hi> whiche haue an other maner more of doynge, and is, in that they put theyr ſtaues be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore them. The ſame alſo is the cuſtome of the <hi>Naſamoniens,</hi> when that any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take a wyfe. The eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pouſed is bounde to preſente hym ſelfe to all them of the feaſt, and to be bounde to them to graunt for to do there pleſure, and he which hath company with her may gyue her a preſence without daunger, and do what he liſt with her. They vſe cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tein othes. They amongeſt theym which be iuſt &amp; of a holly lyfe were had in this reputacion, that after theyr deathe the menne of the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey did reuoke or call ageyne their names, by certeyne obedes, in ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge and touchynge the ſepulcher did tranſport alſo, for to do theyr ſort
<pb facs="tcp:13062:64"/>
and geſſe vpon the Sepulchers of theyr auncitours, and after they had made theyr oracion, they ſlepe vpon the ſame, and do coniectoure vppon that whiche myght come of it, whiche in ſleapynge they drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med fyrſt of The maner of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge which they haue one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is to preſent drynke in token of theyr promes, and if it ſo fortun they haue no drynke, they take the pouder of the earth, and laye it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr tong. There is an other kynd of people in that countreye called <hi>Garamantes</hi> that contrey was tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficked and and traded of other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. They do vſe no weapons, they dare not defende theym ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt other which ſtryue againſt them, they do dwell beyonge the <hi>Naſomoniens</hi> towardes the occide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in part of the ſea. To thoſe people
<pb facs="tcp:13062:65"/>
do ende other which be called <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cez</hi> which do cauſe theyr heare to be ſhorne vpon the top of the head and let it grow in the mids. Theyr neyghbours be <hi>Guydans,</hi> who in theyr warres they make continual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly agaynſt the <hi>Autrices,</hi> do inſteade of other armours, put on onely the ſkinnes of certeyne beſtes. The wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men in theyr apparell hade dyuers borders of furres or ſkynnes. And for this reaſon as it is written for that of euery man who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue had company they toke by a maner of a preſent, a veſtment in ſuch ſort that ſhe whiche is ſo apparelled, was counted moſt horourable, as to beloued of many. The <hi>Machlie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> which be other people inhabyting in the countrey in <hi>Maraiz,</hi> be called <hi>Maraiz Tritonides.</hi> They do were theyr heare behynde, and nothyng
<pb facs="tcp:13062:65"/>
before. The <hi>Auſes</hi> contrawyſe be other people inhabiting in the ſame region, and do weare theyr heare before. The maydens of that countrey do accuſtomablye parte theym ſelues into bandes or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes, and do fyght one agaynſte an other with ſtaues, and caſt ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and doth ſay that this faſhion hath ben by theym obſerued in the honour of theyr goddeſſe <hi>Minerue.</hi> Thoſe whiche were wounded and conſtrained to leaue the fyeld were eſtemed with them whiche remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and reſyſted vnworthye of the honour of the maydens. Contrary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe, ſhe which ſhalbe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted moſt hardieſt, at the ende is apparelled after the beſt ſort they can al deuiſe And moreouer ſhe is armed in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour accordynge to the Grekes, &amp; do weare a helmette, lyke vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:66"/>
come of a cocke, after the maner of the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> And after they haue ſo dreſſed her, they ſet her in a cart and do accompanye her all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Mazais.</hi> The people laſte named haue theyr wyues commen amongeſt them, and do vſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture lyke to beaſtes. So ſoone as theyr wyues haue had a chyld, and nourſed it a tyme vntyll the ſayde chylde haue a lyttle ſtrengthe, the ſame amongeſt theym is called the father. The mother muſt forſake to lyue with the ſayde chylde. And ye ſhall vnderſtande that from .iii. monethes to three monethes, the man hath companye with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and then the mother ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer the chylde to one whome ſhe ſhall pleaſe. The other people of the ſame region which be called <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes,</hi> becauſe they inhabyte to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:13062:66"/>
the mount <hi>Atlas</hi> by <hi>Arom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es,</hi> that is without perticuler name They do deteſt the curſe of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge ſonne, with infinite execraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in that it is ſo hote that it bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth them and theyr region. They eate no kynde of fleſhe, and haue no reſtynge place to ſleape. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people of <hi>Aphrique,</hi> whiche be called <hi>Paſtoriciens</hi> lyue by fleſh and mylke, notwithſtandyng they eate no beafe, no more then the Egipti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens do eate porke: for ther the wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men of the contrey of <hi>Cerene</hi> haue a feare or horroure to beate theyr kynne. becauſe they ſayde beaſtes be offered to theyr god or Idoll <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> the whiche in Egypte is hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and for his honour obſerue cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne faſtyng dayes and holy daies The women of <hi>Barcees</hi> whiche be other people of that countrey haue
<pb facs="tcp:13062:67"/>
a contrary obſeruacion, for they ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer eate bieffe nor porke. And ſo ſone as theyr chyldren be .iiii. or .v. yeres olde, they do beate the vey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of theyr heades, ſome of theim do burne the veygnes of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and that which is ſet burning vpon theyr heades is of bloud and woll, ſet on fyer vppon theyr heare to the entent that the moiſtnes and petuitie deſcendyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the braine and other partes of the head maye not hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by this meanes they ſay theyr chyldren are more health<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and theyr perſons in better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicion. The maner of theyr ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce be theſe, that after they haue cut the eare of a ſhepe, they preſent it in ſigne of thankes geuen for the fyrſt frutes they haue euery yere. They do caſt the ſayde eare vppon the couerynge of theyr houſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:13062:67"/>
done, they do wry theyr ſhepes nec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. They do no other ſacrifices but vnto the ſon and mone. They bury the dead, as the Greekes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Naſamoniens,</hi> when they perceaue that one amongeſt theim is at the point of deathe, beynge in his bed, doth lyft him vp, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him to ſit vpryght, for feare that he ſhulde yelde vp the ghoſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng in his bed vpon his backe. their tabernacles be buylded, and gorgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly made, ſet vpon great trees after ſuche a ſorte, that they wyll turne with euery wynde. The <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iens</hi> do weare theyr heare on the ryght ſyde, and ſhaue away all on the left, they do peynt theyr bodies with red, and they ſay it commeth from the <hi>Troyens.</hi> The women of <hi>Zabiques</hi> be other people, endynge to the <hi>Maxiens</hi> And they do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducte
<pb facs="tcp:13062:68"/>
theyr huſbande cartes whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they go a warfare. The <hi>zigante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be other people of that nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They haue a great quantitie of hony bees that the men by theyr induſtri kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth wel howe to kepe and noriſh them, ſo that they multiply gretly in ſo much there is ſo greate abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance that the people be fedde onely ther with. The people be alſo pein<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted red. All the nacions of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Libie</hi> do lyue a very ſtrange and wylde lyfe, The mooſte part of the day tyme in the ſomer, they goo vnder ſome ſhadowe, ſo that there is no diuerſitie betwene theim and beaſtes, they make no prouiſion for that they lacke. And for theyr apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel they vſe gotes ſkynnes. The mooſt myghtieſt amongeſt theym, haue no cities ſubiecte vnder them but lytle towares al about the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:13062:68"/>
ſyde. In the which they put al their neceſſaries, and that whiche they haue gathered be layde in the ſayde towers. Euery yere they do a kynde of obediens to theyr ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and by that they ſhewe theym ſelues to be frendes to the good and parcecutoures of the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, as theues, and robbers of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treys. Theyr weapons in warre be proper, agreable both for theyr maner and nature, for that they are lyght of bodye, and the countrey plaine for the moſt part therof, they vſe no ſwordes nor daggers, nor no lyke weapons, yet they cary with them iii. dartes, and a quantitie of ſtones which they gather, and put into a lether buget. They be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſuch wepons both for the aſſautynge and retyryng backe that they do hurt greately theyr e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:69"/>
by that ſo longe exercyſe they make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues parfet. They holde no feyth to ſtrangers. The <hi>Troglodites</hi> (whom the Grekes cal herdme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſhepherds becauſe they kepe cattel) be people in <hi>Ethiope</hi> of this ſame region, whiche thorowe out all countreys appointed theym ſelues a kynge. They haue theyr women and chyldren common, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the kyng which hath his wife and chyldren a part. As ſone as the quene his wyfe is come to ſee hym The kynge with all magnificence dothe preſente to her a nomber of cattel. As longe as the wyndes of <hi>Etheſiens</hi> do laſt to the dogge day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. There doth fal in that countrey great plenty of rayne. They are fedde moſt comonly with the blud of beaſtes and mylke myngled ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:13062:69"/>
together. And when that their paſtures be baren becauſe of the heate of the ſonne, they do ſeke for the maryſhes. They haue no wars one with an other, by reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of they lyue lyke lordes. They do kyll theyr olde mottons and thoſe which can not kepe them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maledies and diſſeaſes. They do aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcribe no certeyne name to none of theyr chyldren. For they do thinke that the ſheape and the bulles be theyr fathers and mothers, &amp; why? becauſe from thoſe beſtes they haue theyr dayly noryture. The commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people do vſe to drinke the iuce of a tre called <hi>Aubeſpine</hi> The rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do cauſe to be preſſed a certein kind of flower. The licour whereof ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth drynke for them, hauynge in a maner the taſt of worſe new wine
<pb facs="tcp:13062:70"/>
They leade theyr ſheape frome one place to an other, for feare that the ſayd ſheape ſhold be wery to abyde ſtyll in one countrey. The peoples bodyes be all naked ſauynge theyr members. Whiche they couer wyth ſkynnes. They ſayd <hi>Troglodites.</hi> Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal <hi>Megauares,</hi> do weare alwayes for theyr armour a coote of buffe with heare and al vndeſſed &amp; amaſe ſet wyth poyntes of Iron, other do cary a bowe, another halfe a pycke. They do not paſſe to buyld Tombes and Sepulchers, but in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteade of a tombe, they do burye the bodye of the deade with ſuche lyke woodde as we call ſplynt, or barkes of trees, and the bodye is wrapped therin euen from the top of the head, to the ſoole of the fote. Afterwarde they ſet it in ſome high place, and couereth it with the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:13062:70"/>
they caſt vpon, and that doone they do laughe at the deade. And af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter that they haue couered wyth ſtones they put vpon it a horne of a gote, and ſo leauethe hym without takynge any more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſyon. They make battell one agaynſt an other not in angre or for ambytion (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Grekes were wonte to do) but too gayne the commodytie of theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and fieldes. Fyrſte in theyr warres they caſte at one an other a great nomber of ſtones. And they vſe of a cuſtome to ſhut one at an o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, ſo that theyr foloweth greate blodſhed. Theſe battelles be neuer ended but by the moſt ancient wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the which be in great ſuertie (for that no man of thone parte nor of the other wyll hurte them) they do go betwene two, and ſo do part them whiche be conflicted. They which
<pb facs="tcp:13062:71"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the deſert, and ronne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that countrey for ſhadowe, and do deuower the lytle wyld beaſtes, makynge ſuche courſes, ſometyme dyſtroye manye <hi>Ethiopiens</hi> at theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng out of the maryſſhes, long tyme paſt that nation had ben vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by the Lyons, had not dame nature for ſeane it, and geuen them ſuccours by her prouidence. At the fyrſt entrynge of the dogge dayes, a great multytude of pampyllions, as cater pillers do fley into this councrey, beyng brought without any wynde. The ſame ſwarme of lytle beaſtes doo neuer hurt theym whiche dwell in the maryſſhes. whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wel for mourmuring as for bythynge, do conſtreyne the Lyons to departe. To this nation of <hi>Rirophagis</hi> is ioyned the <hi>Ilopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris</hi> and <hi>Spermatophages.</hi> The laſt
<pb facs="tcp:13062:71"/>
named people lyue of the graynes (as we cal them) the accornes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che fall from the trees in Somer. The reſt of the tyme, they gather certeyne kynde of herbes groynge in theyr orchardes wherof they ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in tyme of hungre. But the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lophagers</hi> with theyr wyfes and chyldren do go into the fyldes and do clyme vp into the trees, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weakeſt branches they dwel ſo well that they maye leape frome one tre to an other lyke as the byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des do, and vpon the ſayde trees they dwell without all daungers. And yf it ſo fortune, that the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhuld ſpreade ouer the weight of theyr bodyes, they holde theym vp with theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: but yf it had ſo chaunced in holdynge vp of thee ſayde braunches they fall vpon the grounde, yet they fallynge, had no
<pb facs="tcp:13062:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:73"/>
harme, becauſe of the agilitie and nimbilnes of their bodyes, beſides all this they lyue of the ſayd trees, choſynge out the tendreſt bowes and do nyble and gnawe the ſame as the lytle mouſe eateth the chiefe, &amp; they ar certyfied with the bark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of trees, Theſe people be alwayes naked, and haue theyr wyfes and chyldren common. They fyght one agaynſte an other, and all to gette others b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e garnyſhed trees &amp; in theyr fyghtes they do vſe no other weapons but of wode, they which be ouercome, be as bonde ſlaues to the vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyſhers or ouer commers. They do oftentymes dye for hungre, or that after they haue ones loſt their ſyght (the whiche fortune to them in leapynge from one tree to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) and cannot ſe to gather that
<pb facs="tcp:13062:73"/>
whiche they vſed to lyue by, then they dye in continent after. The cyrcuit of thys nation is inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by other <hi>Ethiopiens</hi> whiche be called <hi>Cinectens.</hi> There is no dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwene them and the other, for aſmuche as they inhabit in the for reſt countreye, they haue fewe or no fountaynes. They are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to liue vpon the tres becauſe there is ſo many wylde beaſtes, &amp; verye earlye in the mornynge they goo and ſeeke the waters and the fountaines, &amp; do water the braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the trees in the heate of the daye, the wylde Oxen, the Leopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and other wylde beaſtes, doo ronne to the waters for to drynke. And the ſayde beaſtes do drynke ſo muche, that they become ſo heuye &amp; puffed vp that they can not well reſiſt. Then the <hi>Ethiopiens</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:74"/>
frome theyr trees verye fearſly and ſwiftly do aſſault the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well with bournynge ſtaues as alſo with dartes and ſtones. In ſo muche nowe and then they kyll one amongeſte the greate nomber. It chaunſethe ſometyme alſo that the ſayde wylde beaſtes haue the vpper hande and deuoure ſome of the men notwithſtandynge mooſt commenlye there doth come at the laſt, certayne myght and ſtrength ſo that they take the ſaide beaſtes &amp; the rather by there art &amp; induſtry And if it ſhuld hapen that they kyl not theſe beaſtes, but be dryuen to a excigency, then they do in ſuch an extremitie take ageyne the ſkynnes of the ſayd beaſtes, which they had eaten the fleſhe before, do plucke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the heade, ſhoulders with the heare, caſtyng it in water, and with
<pb facs="tcp:13062:74"/>
lytle fire doth ſithe, afterwardes it is deſtrybyted amongeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eat, and are therwith ſertyfied. They vſe theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhote at a but, and gyueth them no meat tyl they hit it, and therby they become good archers, and expert in caſtynge of ſtones. Thereis an other kynde of people in that countreye dwellynge nyghe the deſerte, whiche be called <hi>Archridophages,</hi> and they be verye lowe men and marueylous blacke. At the pryme tyme the wynde of <hi>zephyrus,</hi> &amp; the wynde of <hi>Libique</hi> do brynge out of the deſert a nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of marueilous great Locuſtes, which haue wynges of a lothſome coullour and fygure. The Ethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens beinge accuſtomed &amp; broughte to this, made great a boundaunce of woodes, leaues and ſuche lyke in a longe valley. The ſeaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:13062:75"/>
yere beynge come, that the ſayde beaſtes aboue named were driuen out of the deſert by the ſame wynd and that ſo great aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that a man wolde take them to be clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which paſſed aboue the valley, agayne wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the people, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to theyr maner &amp; cuſtome, dyd put on fyre the ſayd abondau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of woodde couered wyth herbes in the valley the whiche they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heuen &amp; cutte. The ſmoke that aſſended vp frome the ſayde fyre into the ayre, was ſo hote, the locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes flyenge in the myddeſt of the heate, fel downe ded a lytle beyond the ſayde valleye. The quantitie of them is ſo great that they largelye feade and vyttell al the people: And hauynge great ſtore of ſalte in that countreye they do ſalte the ſayd lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes and by that meanes they laſt
<pb facs="tcp:13062:75"/>
longe. And this kynde of meate is plenty and for theyr apetit, that in al their life time they eate nothinge els for they bring vp no beaſtes or cattell in thoſe countreys, nor they haue no fyſhe, becauſe they are far from the ſea &amp; fayre ryuers. They are very lyght, and runne ſwyftly, yet they lyne no longe tyme. They lyue but to the age of forty and no longer. Their endes be not ſo piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as vncredible, for whan they are come to their ful age, that is xl yeres expired. There ingendreth in their bodies certeyne vermines like vnto flees hauyng lytle wynges of diuers colors, &amp; ſo made that they wolde feare a man. Theſe vermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes firſt eateth the belly, then the breſt, and afterwarde by lytle and lytle conſumeth oll the body. They whithe be infected with this mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye,
<pb facs="tcp:13062:76"/>
ſhall at the fyrſt fele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues moued with an iche, and by reaſon of to muche ſcratchynge, there dothe folowe to the parſon aflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a grudging of a newe diſſeaſe with allegement of the fyrſt in a maner. a lytle after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by ſuch Emotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth folowe affluence of bloude whiche commeth out of the bodye of the ſycke patient, that there dothe iſſue in ſpite of him an infinit multitude of the ſayde vermentes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by feleth ſo great payne, that it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fygureth and diſmembreth all his body. And after that it had ſtinted, a freſhe doth iſſue ſuche abondance, of the ſayde bloode and vermentes, that it is vnpoſſyble to helpe hym, in ſomuche eyther by the corrupte eare of the countreye, or beaſtlye bryngyng vp, they ende their lyuea moſt myſerable and peryouſly. The
<pb facs="tcp:13062:76"/>
extremyties of Aphrique towardes the parte of Midy, be in habited w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a kynd of people which the Grekes call <hi>Cynamines</hi> otherwyſe called be the barbarous wylde. They do weare great beardes, and do kepe for theyr defence a nomber of dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for from the middeſt of ſommer to the myddeſt of wynter, there com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>methe into that countreye a multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Oxen from the countrey of Indes. And they knowe not frome whence this plentye ſhulde come, except it be that the ſayde beaſtes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtreaned to fley out of the ſaid region, into this countrey, for feare of the hurt of other wyld beaſtes, or by the iuſtynce of nature. Who hath ingendred many other thynges vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to man, mooſt worthye of admiration, and for that the people be not able to reſyſt ſo great a nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:13062:77"/>
of beaſtes commyng vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be conſtrayned alwayes to haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them ſo great a nomber of dogges, by the help and courſe of the which dogges, there is taken many of the ſayd beaſtes, after they haue kylled them, they eare continent one part, and for their prouiſion ſalt the reſt. They do eat alſo manye other bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes whiche the dogges do werye &amp; kyll. Beyond the aboue ſaid people towardes the Midy, inhabyteth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people whiche they cal <hi>Icthio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phages,</hi> who althoughe they haue the faces of men, yet they dyffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge frome beaſtes in theyr ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges, theſe people dwell vnder the <hi>Troglodites</hi> in the greate ſea <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabie</hi> they be very barbarous. At altymes they be naked, their wifes and chyldren be common, and lyke brute beaſtes, they do not feale any volupe
<pb facs="tcp:13062:77"/>
lupt or paſſion in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues except it be after theyr bodyes feale good or euyll. Theſe people be voyde of diſcretion, good maners, and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye. They dwell in ryuers and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of the ſea along by the waters, and in the hyghe countreyes, in the whiche places be founde many depe caues and longe valleyes. Therbe dyuers narowe holes daungerous at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enteryng &amp; euyl at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge out. In ſo muche that whiche fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, a man may iudg the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey by nature to be made after the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <hi>Icthiophages</hi> for they gathered great heapes of ſtones, &amp; and layed them before the entryng of all croked places, and made more ſuche inuentions for the nettes to take fyſhe of the ſea, becauſe in the ſea whan the flude co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth aboute nonetyde all the place
<pb facs="tcp:13062:78"/>
nighe be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed and cloſed about with waters, and they growe to ſuche an infinite nomber that they couer al the countrey and bringeth a great quantitie of fiſhe, which do ſwyme hither and thyther to fynde theyr paſture, ſo in the ende, at the retournynge agayne of the ſea, the water do caſte theym vp amongeſt the heapes of ſtones, and then the fyſhe lye drie, and they be gathered by the people inhabytynge in that contrey, which do runne with their wyfe and chyldren, and gather the ſayd fiſhes for their prouiſion. And when they dreſſe the ſayde fyſhe to eate, they lay it vpon the ſtones to wardes the Midy, or nontyde, and burnethe it in the heate of the ſonne and doth let it lye vpon the one ſyde a whyle, and turneth the other ſide whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they thinke it is roſted inough
<pb facs="tcp:13062:78"/>
they plucke out all the fleſhe, &amp; put it in a hollowe ſtone, which is lyke vnto a morter, then mixeth it with the grayne of a goſebery tree, or much lyke to it, theſe mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſo well, that it maketh goodly meate to eate, they ſet it in the ſon after they haue put it together they make it lyke in proprietie to a tyle. This they vſe for all theyr meate with great abundance and ioy, and ſeruethe theym inſteade of corne, when it chaunce that the find of the ſea abyde ſtyll and nothynge demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe, by reaſon wherof they were forced to leaue theyr comodytie of fyſhynge, and that they abyde hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Then they heape together the ſhels of the ſea which be veri great and do breake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſtones, and ſo fead of the fleſhe they fynd with in the ſayde ſhelles the whiche is in taſte lyke to an oyſter of the ſea.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:79"/>Ageyne if this kynd of lyuyng wer taken from theym by continuall tempeſtes and wyndes. They take the bones of the fyſhes by theym gathered afore and gnaweth it like a dogge the tender and freſhe. And the hardeſt bone they breake with ſtones. In ſo doynge they dyffer nothynge from beaſtes. This kind of vitell they receyue for theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt with great ioye (as I rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before) ſyngynge and makynge good chere one with an other. And after that euery one of them by the care they haue to get chyldren, do accompany with the fyrſte woman they mete, without hauynge any ſolicitude all theyr lyfe longe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che commeth by reaſon of the afflu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which to theym be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:79"/>
for the ſpace of v. days to that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of lyuynge, the ſyxte daye they go together to fynde the welles to drink, by the way as they go, they crye both in one voyce in ſuche ſorte that a man woulde iudge them ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be the crieng of a multytud of wyld beſtes then mens voyces. As ſoone as they come to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, they receyue in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of water, that they can not wel retourne ageyne, but reſt them ſelues there and can eate no more, beynge afterwarde as men trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled or rather dronken. The next day folowyng they retourne a fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge, and in this ſorte paſſynge theyr lyues (beyng a very fewe of them ſicke) and that is for becauſe they eate but one kynde of meate, yet for al that they liue not ſo longe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:80"/>
this coſt to theyr lodgynge and by the pleaſaunt ſhadowes they are tempr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt vnderſtand that the caues of that countrey, the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue theyr throtes towardes the <hi>Midy</hi> be as hote as a furnaſſe, becauſe of the heate of the ſonne, &amp; conſequently doth folow that they be neuer inhabited: wherfore alme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that contrey doth couer to dwell towardes the Septentrion. Such was the maner and lyuynge of the two <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thiophages.</hi> There reſtethe yet to ſpeke of the <hi>Amazones</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che (as they ſay) in tyme paſt was of one part of <hi>Aphrique</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bie</hi> They were women of warre and of good courage gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differryng frome the women in our age and tyme. A certeyne time of theyr age they were accuſtomed to exercyſe the ſeate of warre, and
<pb facs="tcp:13062:80"/>
by that kept theyr virginitie. After that they had paſſed theyr age, as aboueſayd, they maried huſbands to encreaſe chyldren. They had the prehemines to gouerne all publike matters, for the common weale was ruled by them, in ſuch ſort ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the women, that theyr huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des had the charge of al the domeſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal affayres whiche we accuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commit to our wyues. And the wiues to the contrary ruled as our men do heare, yea, ſo circumſpecte they were, that theyr huſbandes ſhulde not take in hande any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke matter, that they woulde not ſuffer theym once to ſpeke in cauſes touchyng the common weale. So ſone as they be in theyr bed, theyr chyldren be gyuen men to kepe, and they to nourſe them, which infants be brought vp with wylke, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13062:81"/>
meates agreable for theyr age If a woman had ben deliuered of a man chylde he ſhulde haue had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ryght arme broken or ben killed. But if ſhe had brought forth a female or woman chylde, they woulde burne her breſtes with an hote yron for to take away al that which might let her in the warres, and for that cauſe they were called with the Greekes <hi>Amazones:</hi> That is to ſay, women without breſtes. They did inhabite (as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) in an Ilande called <hi>Heſpera,</hi> which was ſo named for that it aprocheth nygh the <hi>Occident,</hi> and is within the lake <hi>Tritonide,</hi> nygh to the <hi>Oce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an</hi> ſea. That lake is ſo called by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ryuer <hi>Triton</hi> whiche paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thorowe the ſame, beyng citu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to <hi>Ethiope</hi> and to the me unt <hi>Atlas,</hi> which is one of the hygheſte
<pb facs="tcp:13062:81"/>
and wydeſt in all that countrey.</p>
            <p>This Ilande is greate, repleniſhed with trees, and a bundance of frute In that countrey is plenty of ſhepe, wherwith moſt of the people be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed and fedde. Wheate is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the inhabiters of that con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, becauſe there neuer grewe none there.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>A generall diſcription of Aphrique. Capi. vii.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>AFrique</hi> is ended on the eſt part with <hi>Nilus</hi> and on the other partes with the ſea. And truely it is ſhorter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Europa,</hi> for it is ſtret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched contrary to no part of <hi>Aſia,</hi> &amp; not to the ſea bankes of all <hi>Europia</hi> and it is more longe then broode &amp; there as it butteth vpon the fludde it is moſt brode, and as it procedeth
<pb facs="tcp:13062:82"/>
fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſe euen ſo ryſyng vp w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſpecially in the middeſt it goeth on croked into the weſt, and ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth it ſelfe eaſely, and therfore by the way is made by lyttle and little narower, and there as his end is it is moſt narowe. For ſo much as is inhabited it is very frutful, but for as much as the moſt partes of it be vnoccupied, &amp; eyther couered with baren landes, or els deſert with the drought of heauen and of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, or els be vexed with manye and miſcheuous kyndes of wylde beaſtes, it is more waſte then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with people The ſee wher with it is gyrded on the north ſyde we do cal <hi>Libicum.</hi> And on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouth <hi>Ethiopicum</hi> and on the weſt <hi>Atlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um.</hi> And on the part that lyethe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>libicum</hi> next drouince vnto <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> is that which we do cal <hi>Cirenas,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:82"/>
and after that is it to whom is gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a name by the vocable of the hole region that is to ſay <hi>Aphrique,</hi> The other partes the <hi>Numides</hi> and the <hi>Murrians</hi> doth holde, but the Murrians are ſet out vnto the ſee <hi>Atlantium</hi> beyonde them be <hi>Nigri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te,</hi> and <hi>Pharuſii.</hi> vnto the <hi>Ethiopes</hi> for they do poſſeſſe the reſidue of it and the hole ſyde that is towardes the ſouth euen vnto the borders of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> And aboue thoſe regions whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are weſhed with the <hi>Libicum</hi> ſee by <hi>Libies Aegiptii</hi> and <hi>Lencothio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> and a nacion verye frequente and manyfolde called <hi>Setuli.</hi> after whom the region is vacant and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitable continually for a greate ſpace. And then the fyrſt on the Eſt as we do heare ſay are <hi>Garamantes</hi> and after them <hi>Augila,</hi> and beyond them <hi>Proglodita,</hi> and laſt of all vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:83"/>
the weſt <hi>Atlantes.</hi> And within if ye lyke to gyue credance are ſuche as be ſcant worthy to be called men, but rather halfe beſtes. <hi>Aegipanes</hi> and <hi>Blemie:</hi> and <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antes</hi> and <hi>Sat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri,</hi> wandrynge without houſes and mancions euerywhere &amp; hath landes rather then inhabiteth them we haue manifeſt to you al thyngs at large, aſwell the nature and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners of the people of <hi>Aphrique,</hi> as alſo the cituacion of theyr nacions and countreys. And heare we wil end the diſcription of this fyrſt part of the world, geuyng the reader my trauaile, aſpectyng and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng for the fortunate ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of acceptacion. And for mine enterpriſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour I craue his good worde.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table">
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:13062:83"/>
               <head>¶ A particuler table conteynynge all the Chapiters in the fyrſt boke of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of the countrey of Aphrique,</head>
               <item>FIrſt The opinion of the devines, touching the original of man.</item>
               <item>The falſe opinion of the Infidels.</item>
               <item>The deuiſion of the worlde into iiii, partes.</item>
               <item>The d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcription of the countrey of Aphrique.</item>
               <item>The diſcription of the countrey of Egypt.</item>
               <item>Of penes and other people inhabytynge in Aphrique.</item>
               <item>A generall diſcription of Aphrique.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ A particuler table of all the notable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in this preſent booke, of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of Aphrique, Capi. i.</head>
               <item>IMprimus the creation of heauen &amp; earth.</item>
               <item>The creation of man.</item>
               <item>The couplynge of man and wyfe.</item>
               <item>The touchynge of the arke vpon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of Armenie.</item>
               <item>Cayne the fyrſt begotten.</item>
               <item>Abell the ſeconde.</item>
               <item>Noyes arke holy.</item>
               <item>The diſparſynge of mankynde abrode in the worlde.</item>
               <item>Howe Noye ſent his chyldren to inhabite the partes of the earth.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Capitulo .ii.</head>
               <item>The worſhihpynge of the ſonne and moone as goddes.</item>
               <item>The falſe perſwaſion of the philoſophers for the creation of man.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13062:84" rendition="simple:additions"/>Howe ſome phyloſophers beleued that man is incorruptible, ſome corruptible, and without takynge begynnynge.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Capitulo .iii.</head>
               <item>The deuicion from the weſt is called hemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheris, and hath .v. diſtinct zones.</item>
               <item>The ſtrayght entrynge is called fretum.</item>
               <item>The ſpredynge abrode is called helles po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Capitulo .iiii.</head>
               <item>There be in Ethiope many collored people.</item>
               <item>Howe the Ethiopiens take them ſelues fyrſte procrreated of the mortalles.</item>
               <item>What the figures ſignifieth of Milan, Crocodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le and locil</item>
               <item>Theyr kynges lyue after theyr lawes made.</item>
               <item>Howe the kynge ſignifieth death to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactours.</item>
               <item>The due honour that the Ethiopiens do attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to theyr kynge, and howe they wyſhe thyr kynges diſeaſe to them ſelues as often as he ſhalbe ſycke.</item>
               <item>The people be all naked.</item>
               <item>The people lyue with herbes and rootes.</item>
               <item>Meroe is the capitall towne in that tountrey.</item>
               <item>Macrobiens be people in Ethiope whiche do eſteme rather lether and tynne then golde.</item>
               <item>Howe kynge Cambiſes embaſſadours, came cheyned lyke priſoners in cheynes of golde from that countrey</item>
               <item>There groweth precious ſtones.</item>
               <item>Aubeſpine is a goſebery tree.</item>
               <item>Howe the people worſhyp as gods the ſonne and mone.</item>
               <item>He is choſen kynge that can ſkyll beſt to kepe beaſtes.</item>
               <item>Theſe people beleue that there is an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge
<pb facs="tcp:13062:84"/>
God. And ageine ſay they there ſhuld be another mortall.</item>
               <item>The Pretian or Preſte Iohn is kynge and of a greate blud, and hath thre ſcore and two kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vnder him.</item>
               <item>They haue the epiſtles of ſayncte Paule and certeyne religious houſes.</item>
               <item>Preſthod is the chiefe and hygheſt degree of dignitie.</item>
               <item>The ſharpe puniſhement for aduultrers.</item>
               <item>There is dyuers kynde of language amongeſt them.</item>
               <item>The people of Libie folowe the errour of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet.</item>
               <item>A lake which they are waſſhed in ſhyne lyke to oyle.</item>
               <item>Maruelous byrdes as Tragopomones, and Pagaſi.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Capitulo .v.</head>
               <item>There be dumme people beyonde the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans haye.</item>
               <item>Thebes and Abido, Babilon, and other great Cities in Egypt.</item>
               <item>A ryuer called Nile.</item>
               <item>Howe the women voyde theyr vryne agaynſt a walle.</item>
               <item>The vſages of the Egiptians in theyr letters.</item>
               <item>The Egyptians be great Idolaters.</item>
               <item>The reuerenes of the yonger to the elder.</item>
               <item>The kynges of Egypt holde not theyr wylles for lawes.</item>
               <item>The ſolitudenes and carefulnes of the kinges of Egypt, to haue prudent councellers aboute them.</item>
               <item>The due iuſtice of the kynges of Egypt</item>
               <item>The atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiuenes of the kynges to the petici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:13062:85"/>
of the poore, and howe they wyll heare the poores cauſes them ſelues.</item>
               <item>How the people of Egypt pray for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion of theyr kynge.</item>
               <item>Lawes made to auoyde Ebrietie &amp; pronkenes.</item>
               <item>The obediens of the Egiptians towardes the mageſtrates.</item>
               <item>The lamentacion of the people for the deathe of a iuſt kynge.</item>
               <item>The diſtribucion of the reuenewes of the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges landes.</item>
               <item>Howe euery man lyueth accordynge to theyr vocacion.</item>
               <item>The punyſhement apointed for malefactours</item>
               <item>They which be choſen rulers be prudent and Wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</item>
               <item>A cheyne of golde ſignifienge veritie.</item>
               <item>The ſentence of the iudge pronounced.</item>
               <item>The punyſhement apointed for periurers</item>
               <item>The greuous puniſhement appointed for the paradice and manſleer.</item>
               <item>The peyne for clyppers of money.</item>
               <item>The lawes made for rauiſhers of the free woman.</item>
               <item>Abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is the beſt diet &amp; medicine for man.</item>
               <item>The eſtate of mariage.</item>
               <item>The expence the parentes is at with the child is xx d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>achemes, that is .x. s</item>
               <item>The puniſhement apointed for the phiſition if the ſicke patient ſhulde dye.</item>
               <item>The feadynge of theyr ſacrificial beaſtes is wonderfull.</item>
               <item>The ſepulcher is denied the vſerer.</item>
               <item>Howe the Egiptians abhorre vſery.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Capitulo. vi.</head>
               <item>Adrimachides be people in aphrique amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:13062:85"/>
the puniciens.</item>
               <item>Naſemoniens robbers on the ſea.</item>
               <item>Theſe people be vnnaturall and lyke beaſtes.</item>
               <item>Meſagetes put theyr ſtaues before them.</item>
               <item>Howe he which was iuſt hath ben in reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</item>
               <item>The fourme of promiſynge one an other.</item>
               <item>Garamatea other people in Aphrique.</item>
               <item>Macez clyppeth away the heare in the toppe of the heade,</item>
               <item>Autruces theyr wyues haue dyuers bordera of furres, and why they weare ſuch borders.</item>
               <item>Machliens be people in Aphrique.</item>
               <item>Auſes be other people and weare al theyr heare before</item>
               <item>Howe the maydes fyght in the honor of their Goddeſſe minerue.</item>
               <item>Atlantes be people amongeſte the Punitiens, theſe people haue no perticuler names.</item>
               <item>Paſtoriciens be people that lyue by fleſhe &amp; mylke.</item>
               <item>Howe the women of Cerene feare to hurt the cattel which ſhulde be offred to theyr Idoll Iſis.</item>
               <item>Howe the women of Barcees eate no beafe nor porke, and alſo howe they burne the vey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the temples of theyr chyldren.</item>
               <item>A ſtrange maner of ſacrifice they do.</item>
               <item>Howe theſe people wyll not ſuffer a perſone to lye dyenge vpon his backe.</item>
               <item>Theyr churches be made to turne lyke to a vane to and fro with euery wynde,</item>
               <item>The zigantes be people of that nacion &amp; haue great ſtore of hony bees.</item>
               <item>In theyr warres ech one cary .iii. dartes and ſſones.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13062:86"/>Troclodites be people in Aphrique, theyr wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and chyldren be common,</item>
               <item>They haue neuer warres.</item>
               <item>Megauares be people which haue warres, &amp; theyr warres be neuer ended but by the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient women,</item>
               <item>Theſe people deſyre rather to dye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lyue Rizophages be people that haue greate ſtore of Pampilions in theyr countrey.</item>
               <item>Ilophagris and Spermatophages be people in Aphrique.</item>
               <item>Howe theſe people make them houſes, vppon trees.</item>
               <item>After what ſort theſe people dye for hunger.</item>
               <item>Cineciens be people in Ethiope.</item>
               <item>Howe the Ethiopiens kyll the Lions, Leparda and other wylde beaſtes.</item>
               <item>Theyr prouiſion in tyme of hunger.</item>
               <item>Howe theyr chyldren eate no meate vntyl they ſhute and hyt a but.</item>
               <item>Acridophages be lowe men and blacke</item>
               <item>There be great ſtore of locuſtes brought in by certeyne wyndes.</item>
               <item>The wytty practiſe they exerciſe to diſtroye theſe locuſtes.</item>
               <item>¶ A wonderfull thynge to beholde howe they ende theyr lyues.</item>
               <item>Howe they lyue but vntyll the age of xl. yeres</item>
               <item>what vermines engender in theyr bellies</item>
               <item>Cinamines barbarous people, they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a company of dogges with them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the wylde beaſtes from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</item>
               <item>Icthiohhages be people lyttle differyng from beaſtes.</item>
               <item>Howe the fyſhe be caſt vp vpon the rockes &amp;</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13062:86"/>Theyr prouiſion in tyme of hunger.</item>
               <item>Howe the men and women crye lyke beaſtes,</item>
               <item>They can endure and abyde hunger by nature</item>
               <item>They neuer drynke.</item>
               <item>Howe theſe people wylle ſuffer ſtripes verye delectable to reade.</item>
               <item>All the caues towardes the Midy be hote.</item>
               <item>Amazones were women of warre, and take vpon them to meddell in publyke affayres</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="lists">
            <list>
               <head>¶ A table of the diſcription of Aſye, and Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropie, the other two partes of the worlde, with the perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler nacions.</head>
               <item>Of Aſie the ſeconde part of the worlde.</item>
               <item>Of Panchaye.</item>
               <item>Of Aſyrie</item>
               <item>Of Iudee.</item>
               <item>Of Medie.</item>
               <item>Of Parthye.</item>
               <item>Of Perſe. ¶ ¶</item>
               <item>Of Indes.</item>
               <item>Of Scithie.</item>
               <item>Of Vartarie.</item>
               <item>Of Turquie</item>
               <item>Of Chriſtendone ¶ ¶</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Eropia.</head>
               <item>Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rice</item>
               <item>Of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cye.</item>
               <item>Of Laconie or Lacedemonie.</item>
               <item>Of Crete.</item>
               <item>Of Tharrace.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13062:87"/>Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or Ruthenie</item>
               <item>Of Lithuanie.</item>
               <item>Of Liuonie.</item>
               <item>Of Polo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne.</item>
               <item>Of Hungry.</item>
               <item>Of Boeſme.</item>
               <item>Of Allmanye.</item>
               <item>Of ſaxone</item>
               <item>Of weſtualie</item>
               <item>Of franconie.</item>
               <item>Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uenie.</item>
               <item>Of Bauier.</item>
               <item>Of Italy.</item>
               <item>Of Ligurie.</item>
               <item>Of the Coſcane.</item>
               <item>Of Galatie.</item>
               <item>Of Fraunce</item>
               <item>Of Spayne.</item>
               <item>Of Portyngale.</item>
               <item>Of Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de, scotlande, and Irelande,</item>
               <item>Of the vle of Taprobane.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Finis,</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Fleteſtrete at the ſigne of the George next to ſaynt Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones Churche by Wyllyam Powel</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13062:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
